欢迎收看斯坦福大学公开课
本字幕由志愿者义务贡献
Welcome to Stanford CS193P,this is winter quarter 2015.
欢迎参加斯坦福大学2015年冬季学期的 CS193P 课程。
And we're gonna dive right in today to some brief slide work.
我们首先简要地概览一下今天课程的内容。
This people at Stanford, you've got a document that describe, describes all the grading and all that stuff
在座的同学，你们手里都有一份叙述评分标准的文档，
so I'm not gonna go over that in lecture like I often do to start the quarter.
所以我不想像以往开课时那样再复述一遍。
Instead I'm gonna talk a little bit about, what this class is about.
相反，我首先要谈一谈，这门课到底是讲什么的。
Brief mention of the prerequisites cuz they're pretty important in this class.
接下来简单提一下学习本课程的先决条件，这个事对于课程挺重要的。
Then just the quickest overview of iOS.
然后会对 iOS 进行一个快速的预览。
I'm gonna assume that anyone who is here or is watching this, knows what that is.
我想在座的和观看视频的各位同学都知道那是什么吧。
And then, we're gonna dive right into a big old demo.
再然后，会带领大家做一个大的 demo。
It's gonna be a two-day thing, where I'm really going to try and
这个 demo 会讲两节课，在这期间我会
introduce you to Xcode and the development environment and
向你们介绍开发 iOS 需要用到的
this language Swift, that you're gonna have to learn to develop for iOS.
集成开发工具 Xcode 和编程语言 Swift。
All right, so what is this class about?
那么本课程是讲什么的呢？
It's about building cool apps, as we know.
这门课讲述的是开发超 cool 的 iOS 应用。
Why are these iOS apps so cool?
为什么这些 iOS 应用这么 cool 呢？
Well, because the device you're gonna run them on is in your pocket or
因为运行这些应用的设备要么在你的口袋里，
in your backpack.
要么在你的背包里。
Either, if you write an app, you can just pull it out and show your friends and
如果你写了一个应用，你可以将它展示给你的朋友，
it's highly networked and incredible graphics with animation.
它高度集成网络，并有惊艳的动画图形效果。
It's just cool all the way around and I think you guys all know that or you wouldn't be here.
它在各个方面都很 cool。我想你们应该都知道这些，否则你们就不会坐在这里了。
But you're also gonna learn in this class a lot of real life Object-Oriented Programming.
在这们课程中，你们也需要学习一些关于面向对象编程的知识。
You're taking a lot of other classes here at Stanford on things like graphics, and
你们也可能在斯坦福参加过一些关于图形、
networking, and databases, and maybe animation. Things like that.
网络、数据库也许还有动画方面的课程。
And we're gonna is kinda tie that all together into a real world class.
然而我们将这些内容融合在一起，
'Kay? You're gonna get to see all this stuff.
你们会在本课程内看到所有这些东西。
Now, you know, it's gonna be kind of a survey course in that,
现在，你应该知道这会是一个概述型课程，
I can't go too deep into networking. I can't go too deep into databases.
我不会深入讲述网络的内容，我不会深入讲述数据库的内容，
I can't go too deep into animation, but you'll get to see it all in a really real
我不会深入讲述动画的内容，但是你们会在
world environment, where people out there building apps using that technology.
真实项目的环境中用到所有的这些技术。
For some of you who haven't seen that before that'll be a big bonus of this class, I think.
我认为，对于一些之前没有接触过这些的同学，本课程对他们会有很大的提升。
The prerequisites of this class.
学习本课程的先决条件。
Number one thing is you have to be a pretty strong Object-Oriented programmer.
最重要的，你要是一个很给力的面向对象开发者。
If you're not a strong Object-Oriented programmer, and
如果你不是，
you hit this class, you're probably gonna go under water, pretty quick.
还选了这个课，你可能很快就会掉队了。
Okay? I'm gonna assume you know, everything about Object-Oriented Programming.
我假设你已经了解关于面向对象编程的一切。
iOS is a completely Object-Oriented Programming envir, development environment.
iOS 是一个完全的面向对象编程的开发环境。
I just don't mean I'm not just talking about the language is Object-Oriented.
我的意思不只是说编程语言是面向对象的。
But the entire design of it the way you use it if you're not
在你使用过程中，它的整个设计方式都是面向对象的。如果你
comfortable with things like subclassing and
不熟悉类似于子类之类的东西，
stuff like that then you're just really gonna be behind the curve.
那么你真的有可能离挂科不远了。
In iOS so at Stanford here that means CS16A and B or
斯坦福编程相关课程有 CS16A、CA16B、
CS16X, and then you know, CS107, while it's not really Object-Oriented course,
CS16X、以及 CS107，虽然它并不是专门的面向对象课程，
at least it's a heavy duty programming course.
但至少是一门重量级的编程课程。
CS108 is a great Object-Oriented course so
CS108 是非常好的面向对象课程，所以
if you have, if you've taken CS108 you'll probably, be really well prepped.
如果你曾经参加过 CS108，你可能会觉得很轻松。
110, again not really too much an Object-Oriented program but
110，同样也没有太多关于面向对象的知识，
good programming course cuz there's a lot of programming in this class,
但同样是一门非常好的编程课程，因为其中有大量的编程实践。
in fact, all the work in this class is programming.
事实上，所有这些课程的内容都是关于编程的。
You will not have, a little bit of reading the first couple of weeks just to
在头几个星期，你们需要为了学习新语言，多做一些阅读。
kinda learn this new language, but it's almost all programming after that all
在这之后，一直到最终的项目，
the way til the end, including your final project.
都需要运用到你新学到的语言进行编程任务。
So if you're not really comfortable with all these terms,
所以，如果你真的不适应面向对象编程，
this Object-Oriented terms or if you're just not really comfortable with
或者你真的不太适应写较大的程序，
writing big programs then this class will definitely be a challenge for you.
那么这门课程对你来说将是一个巨大的挑战。
okay, so what's in iOS, what are the parts of it?
那么，iOS 都包括哪些部分呢？
You know, it's ha, it's such a big system, it's got so much in it.
它是一个庞大的系统，其中包含很多部分。
It's impossible for me to, like, encapsulate it into a small little summary but.
不太可能能用一两句话将其表述完整。
I do have this slide right here that divides it into these four layers.
我在这个课件中，将其分为四层。
These four layers are approximately down near the hardware at the bottom.
这四层从靠近硬件的底层，
Up near the user at the top. Okay?
到靠近用户的顶层。
So at the bottom, so
在最下面一层，
a lot of people don't realize that iOS is basically a Unix-based operating system.
很多人没有注意到，iOS 基本就是一个基于 Unix 的操作系统。
'Kay? It's very similar shares a lot of the core of Mac OS X. Okay?
它大量借鉴了 Mac OS X 的内核部分。
Now, it's certainly optimized for mobile devices, which have
当然，它专门为在电池等等方面受到限制的移动设备优化过的，
battery restrictions and things like that, but that is basically what it is.
但基本上它仍可看作是一个 Unix 系统。
And so down at that layer you've got sockets, and
这样的话，在这层中包含了 socket、
you've got you know, permissions, and things like that,
permission 等等类似的部分。
that have to be near the oh you know, hardware to, to work properly.
它靠近底层硬件，并保证其正常工作。
But above that there's kind of an Object-Oriented layer that lets you get at
在这之上，是一个能够让你使用大量的面向对象编程技术的
a lot of that stuff using Object-Oriented Programming.
面向对象的层。
'Kay? And this stuff is not UI oriented it's
但是这层不包含 UI
more kind of accessing the hardware through Object-Oriented Programming or
其更多用于通过面向对象的编程方式访问硬件，
accessing networking through Object-Oriented Programming but
或者访问网络，等等。
it's a big layer there and so we will spend a fair amount of
它是一个很大的层，我们将花大量时间在该层上，
time in this layer because we need those primitives to build at the higher layers.
因为我们需要这些原始组建来建立更高的层。
Then, there's this whole layer, which I wish we had more time to spend on.
我希望我们有更多时间花在这一层，
We only get ten weeks in this whole class.
但是我们的课程只有十周。
It goes by so fast, you'll be amazed, as you're probably, used to with your Stanford courses.
在斯坦福的课程中，你会感叹时间过得如此之快。
But there's a whole media layer here, both for
再往上，是一整个媒体层，
static images, as you know, JPEG and things like that.
包括比如你们熟悉的 JPEG 等的静态图像，
And video both capturing video, editing video, all that.
包括拍摄视频、编辑视频等的视频处理，
Incredible audio, the frameworks on this device for doing 3D audio for games and all that.
不可思议的音频框架，用于处理3D音效，以及游戏等等。
I get to, unfortunately I get to very little of this layer.
很不幸，我对这层知道的并不多。
But I'll try to let you know, that it's in there and then you'll know to go out and
但是我可以告诉你它里面有什么，这样你用到的时候就可以查阅相关资料，
seek out, if you're building a very audio intensive app or
或者当你正在写一个用到大量音频视频技术的应用的时候，
video intensive app, you'll seek out that layer.
你会知道去哪找这些资料。
But we'll spend the vast majority of our time at the Cocoa Touch layer.
我们会在 Cocoa Touch 层上花费大量的时间。
So the Cocoa Touch layer, that's where the buttons and
Cocoa Touch 层里包含了 button，
sliders and things like that are it's the layer,
slider 等类似的控件，
where you're gonna build the interactivity with your end user.
通过它们来和你的用户建立互动。
And so, that's where we probably spend 70 plus percent of our time in the Cocoa Touch layer.
我们会在 Cocoa Touch 上花费70%甚至更多的时间。
And this is a very powerful layer.
这也是一个非常强大的层。
You know, you've seen things like the maps app on the phone.
你们可能在手机上见过地图类的应用。
There's basically, an object that does almost the entire maps app, that you can
基本上，有一个几乎完整的地图应用对象，
just drop right into your program, and now you have maps in your program.
你只需要直接拖进你的程序里，你的程序中就有地图了。
Same thing with web browser.
同样的还有浏览器。
If you wanna put web browsing in your app, it's just boom, pop an object in there,
如果你想让你的应用有浏览网页的功能，那么仅仅需要拖拽一个对象，
call a couple methods and in your, on your way.
再调用几个方法即可。
So very powerful, very high level in there's a lot going on in there and
所以在强大和高级的 Cocoa Touch ，我们会了解很多，
that's where we will spend most of our time, 'kay?
并且在此花费大量的时间。
And by the way, if you have any questions I try to glance up, so
顺便说一下，我抬眼一瞥的时候，
the bright lights over there sometimes in my way,
有可能会看到你们的提问，但是有时我也会注意不到，
but, shout out or you know, otherwise get my attention.
所以尽量让我注意到你。
If you feel free to interrupt.
如果你感觉打断我没什么问题的话。
Then there's the development platform itself.'Kay?
接下来就是开发平台本身。
With the tools we use to build these iOS apps.
我们会用这些工具来搭建 iOS 应用。
What's in that?
那么问题来了。其中都有什么？
Well, it's all pretty much now been funneled into this one application called Xcode 6.
有很多很棒的工具都集成在 Xcode 6 内。
There are some little adjuncts that it calls out to but
可能还有其它一些辅助编程工具，
Xcode 6 is everything, it's your code editor,
但是 Xcode 6，你值得拥有，它是一个代码编辑器，
it's your compiler, your debugger all of that in one, pretty awesome app.
它是一个编译器，是一个调试器，总之是一个很棒的应用。
And so we'll be learning all about Xcode 6 in this class, and
所以我们这个课程里会讲到很多有关 Xcode 6 的知识。
that's where you'll be spend all your time developing, you're not gonna be at
而你编程的时候会一直使用 Xcode，你不需要
a terminal typing in Emacs or something, you're gonna be in Xcode 6.
在终端下用 Emacs 或其他的编辑器，你只需要使用 Xcode 6。
Languages I have there's actually, two languages in iOS now.
现在可以使用两种语言开发 iOS 应用。
There are peers that you can pretty much use either one.
你可以选择使用任何一个。
One of them is called Objective-C,
其中一个名为 Objective-C，
that's the language that iOS was originally developed for.
它也是 iOS 一直以来使用的开发语言。
It's a language been around a long time, probably 30 years it's been around or 25
这个语言已经有大概25到30年的历史了，
to 30 years that's it's actually been used to build stuff that's on the Mac today.
人们用它为 Mac 开发应用。
So, it's very mature language but it's also 25, 30 years old.
因此，它是非常成熟的语言，但是已经25，30岁了。
And so Apple last summer introduced a completely new language called Swift, and
所以苹果公司在去年夏天发布了一个叫 Swift 的全新的语言，
Swift, you can do pretty much everything in iOS with Swift，
你可以使用 Swift 在 iOS 上开发任何应用，
that's the language we're gonna learn because it's a modern language.
它也是本次课我们要学习的语言，它是一门现代的语言。
Apple did a great job of kind of, building all the best stuff of
为了创建Swift，苹果公司做了很多工作，
all the languages that have been invented over the last, you know,
它吸收了很多已存在的编程语言的优点。
25 years of this especially the last five or ten years into this language.
二十五年以来，特别是近五到十年的语言的优点。
It's very concise it's a very type safe language but has type inference and a lot
它语法简洁，类型安全的，并且还有类型推断以及
of things that make it so that you get the best of both worlds by having type safety-
大量的特性使鱼与熊掌可以兼得。既有安全的类型
And not have to be constantly over specifying everything.
又不需要不断地指定各种类型。
So we're gonna go Swift only, I'm not even gonna really talk about Objective-C,
所以我们只使用 Swift，不会讲太多 Objective-C，
I just don't have time to do both languages.
我也没有时间讲两种语言。
Yeah. >> [INAUDIBLE] This is
（学生提问）
a [INAUDIBLE] course [INAUDIBLE] [COUGH] [INAUDIBLE] doing iOS development.
>> Yeah, so the question is if I'm going out into the world to do
这个同学的问题是，如果我将步入社会，
iOS development in the real world for real companies.
并想找一份做 iOS 开发的工作，
Am I probably, gonna have to learn Objective-C?
我是否还需要学习 Objective-C？
And the answer is [NOISE] it depends on the company you're at.
答案是，这取决于你的公司。
Probably in the short term, yes.
可能在短期内，答案是肯定的。
But as the time goes by probably, more and more people switch to siff, Swift.
但是随着时间的推移，可能有越来越多的人会转到 Swift。
The good thing is the underlying iOS
好消息这两门语言在 iOS 之下的 API
APIs are exactly the same for both, its just the syntax-
是完全相同的，
Of the language a little bit
仅仅只是语法上
about how the language approaches calling the API is slightly different, but any,
会有略微的不同，但是
everything that you learn in here about the underlying,
你们在这里学习的 iOS 之下的部分，
lying parts of iOS will totally work in Objective-C.
使用 Objective-C 完全也可以实现。
All the methods are the same you know,
所有的方法都是一样的，
it's just the syntax is a little different.
仅仅只有语法上的一点区别。
So, don't feel too bad about not
所以对于没有学全两门语言，
learning both languages, and once you've learned this language,
不要感到沮丧。一旦你掌握了 Swift，
learning Objective-C is gonna be pretty easy, too.
再学 Objective-C 也只是分分钟的事。
So. Good question though. All right.
这个问题问得很好。
Of course iOS is filled with tons of frameworks.
当然，iOS 内部拥有众多的框架，
Frameworks are libraries, basically, of objects that you use,
框架就是你会用到的类库以及基本对象。
as building blocks to build your application.
作为搭建你的应用的模块，
And we are going to be covering them.
我们也会学习它们。
UIKit is the main one.
UIKit 就是其中主要的一个。
It's got most of the user interface stuff in it.
它包含了大量的关于用户界面的内容。
Foundation is that most the course services layer that I was talking about,
在 Core Service 中，我提及最多的就是 Foundation 框架。
and but there's tons of other ones, Core Motion for doing the, the device moving
其他还有很多，Core Motion 框架用于处理设备移动、
around, you know, gyro and accelerometer, Core Data for Object-Oriented database.
旋转、陀螺及加速度等响应，Core Data 框架用于操作面向对象的数据库，
Things like that.
等等。
So I'll get to, as many as those as I can, especially the big ones.
我会尽我所能尽可能多的传授给你们，特别是那些大的框架。
But there's just way too many to cover in ten weeks.
但是这对一个只有十周的课，显得太多内容了。
And finally we I, I put this, as a first class thing with all the rest, as a design strategy MVC.
然而以上的那些东西均不是我们第一课要讲的内容。我首先要说的是一个叫做 MVC 的设计模式。
I think, I usually ask, I'll all ask this year, too.
每年我都会问，同样今年我也要问这个问题，
How many people have used MVC in some other class?
你们有多少同学曾经在其他课上用过 MVC？
See, so it's half of you.
哦，有一半的同学。
So I'll be teaching MVC, as if you don't know it, so
有同学不知道，那么我先说说 MVC。
if you don't know it don't worry.
就算你不了解它，也不用担心。
But MVC is a way of designing your application so that it's a little more
MVC 是你设计应用的一种方式，用它设计的代码
debuggable, reusable understandable to you and to anyone reading your code.
无论对于你自己或者其他人都具有可读性，也更易调试，易复用。
And iOS was designed with MVC from the start.
而 iOS 从一开始就使用MVC设计。
So it's just integral part to building an iOS.
而这仅仅是创建一个 iOS 应用整体中的一部分。
Now, I'm gonna do the demo today, and on Wednesday I'm kinda not gonna follow MVC.
我要开始做今天的 demo。而在周三不会使用 MVC。
But then next Monday we're gonna apply MVC to the demo I'm doing today and
但是下周一我会应用 MVC 继续今天的 demo，
Wednesday, so you're gonna get the full MVC treatment there.
周三的时候你们就会对 MVC 有了充分的理解。
And I'll be having some slides on MVC on Wednesday to prepare you for next Monday.
然后在周三我会放一些 MVC 的课件来为下周一做准备。
Okay? All right, so here's the demo.
好，下面开始做 demo。
The demo I'm gonna do, is something I actually did a few years ago that really works well-
接下来我要做的 demo，是我前几年做的，运行起来还不错的计算器。
With Swift, which is a calculator.
我们用 Swift 来实现它。
So, we're gonna build this calculator.
现在，我们来创建这个计算器。
And we're gonna build it from scratch, all the way.
我们将从头开始，一步一步创建它。
And I like to do my demos, where I only type in stuff, I don't copy and
我喜欢动手敲代码来做演示，而不会复制或者
paste big chunks of code in or whatever.
粘贴大段代码什么的。
I know, I'd see a lot of laptops open, a lot of people like to try and
我知道，我看到很多人已经打开笔记本电脑，很多人都喜欢
follow along with me.
跟着我亲自动手尝试。
I'm a fast typer, but usually in most demos you can keep, keep up if you want.
我打字速度很快，但是通常在大多数演示中，只要你想，还是能够跟上我的速度。
I don't recommend it necessarily, or certainly I don't require it.
我并不推荐这么做，或者说不必要这样。
I am going to, you, you'll be able to go back and watch this particular demo on video.
你们可以回去单独看这个演示视频。
Even Stanford people will be able to do that.
即使是斯坦福的学生也可以这么做。
Because your first assignment is gonna be to reproduce what I do.
因为你们的第一次作业是要重现我所做的。
'Kay? That is 90% of your first assignment.
这就是你第一次作业的90%。
Reproduce what I'm gonna do, today and on Wednesday.
重现我今天和星期三做的。
So I'm not gonna post the code because I want you to go through the experience of
我不会将代码给你，因为我想让你经历自己动手敲代码的过程。
typing the code in, and if you watch in on video,
如果你是在看这个视频，
watching what I do again, and and typing it all in. 'Kay?
再看一遍我干了什么，然后自己敲代码。
And I'll explain that all on Wednesday. Okay?
我将在周三对所有问题做解释。
So, I put on the slide a bunch of things that I'm gonna cover, but I'm not gonna go
我把一些将要提及的部分放到了课件里，但我不会提前
over it in advance, I'm just gonna sit, sit and soon I'll start doing it.
给你们讲这些内容。我要坐下，然后开始演示。
So any questions before I dive in here?
在这之前还有什么问题吗？
I know we're gonna little fast, but I wanna maximize your learning time.
我知道我讲的有点快，因为我想最大化你们的学习时间。
[INAUDIBLE] [NOISE].
（同学提问）
Direct of what?
什么？
Recommendation to which Xcode-
（同学提问）
So the question is, which Xcode should we use, should you use?
那么问题来了，我们应该用哪个版本的 Xcode？
Well, you should just use the one on the Mac App Store.
你们直接使用在 Mac App Store 上的那个版本就好了。
So, just go to the Mac App Store, it's free.
去 Mac App Store 上免费下载。
Use the one there, whatever the latest one is.
使用那里的最新的版本。
If a new one comes out in the quarter, well, let's all switch over to it.
如果有更新的版本出来，那么我们就更新。
Okay, let's just always be using the latest Xcode.
总之我们用的是最新版本的 Xcode。
'Kay any-
还有问题吗？
[INAUDIBLE] Beta [INAUDIBLE] No.
（同学提问）
Not. We're not gonna using a beta or anything like that.
不，我们不用测试版或者类似的一些版本。
We'll just use whatever the currently published Xcode is.
我们只用当前最新的 Xcode 的发布版本。
Okay.
OK
So, I'm going to start this demo actually by launching Xcode.
那么我要开始运行 Xcode 来演示了。
So, here it is, right here. Xcode.
额，这，在这。Xcode。
And when you launch Xcode, let's hide others here.
运行 Xcode 以后，我们把其他东西隐藏起来。
You're gonna get this splash screen and
你会看到这个欢迎界面，
on this splash screen on the right, this is gonna be all your projects.
在欢迎界面的右边，将显示你所有的项目。
Now, since it's the beginning of the quarter, we don't have any projects yet,
由于这是本学期开始，我们还没有任何的项目。
but they'll all be listed here, so as the quarter goes by this will fill up.
但是慢慢的，我们会逐渐将这个列表填满。
You can turn this splash screen off, if you don't like it by the way.
如果你不喜欢这个欢迎页面，可以将它关闭。
This splash screen also lets us do things like playgrounds and
欢迎界面中也可以创建例如 playground，
a source code management right down here.
或者源代码管理，在这里。
We're not gonna be doing that for a while.
我们在很长一段时间内不会碰那些。
We're gonna be focusing on this option, right here.
我们需要关注的是这个选项，这里。
Create a new Xcode project.
创建一个新的 Xcode 项目。
If you don't have the splash screen, you can go to File > New > Project. Kay.
如果你看不到欢迎界面，你也可以 File > New > Project。
Same thing, those both the same thing.
一样的，它们都是一样的。
So I'm gonna click right here on Create a new project.
下面我点击这里，创建一个新项目。
When I create a new project, it wants to know what kind of project you want to create,
当我创建新项目的时候，它需要知道你想创建什么类型的项目。
because Xcode is actually used on Mac OS X and to build frameworks and all that stuff.
Xcode 可以被用于在 Mac OS X 上创建框架，以及所有类似的东西。
But we're always gonna be building iOS Applications.
但是我们将要创建的是 iOS 应用。
And in fact, we're always gonna use this template right here,
事实上，我们经常用到这里的模板，
Single View Application.'Kay?
Single View Application。
That's kind of your basic MVC starter application and
这就是你的基础 MVC 入门应用。
we're gonna build very complicated apps out of that, but we're gonna start here,
我们会用其他这些创建非常复杂的应用，但是我们从这里开始。
so you always click on that one.
所以你会经常点这个。
Then it wants to know what you want to call your app, and
你需要填写应用的名称，
we're building a calculator, so we're gonna call our app, Calculator.'Kay?
我们在创建的是计算器应用，所以我们给它起名为，Calculator。
This organization name doesn't really matter that's just gonna appear in
orgnization 并不重要，它只会出现在
copyright notice and the code that you write at the top in a comment so
类似版权信息，或者你的代码开头的注释中，所以
don't worry about that.
不用管它。
But this organization identifier that is very important.
但是这里的 organization identifier 是非常重要的。
'Kay, this uniquely identifies you. Okay?
它是你的唯一标识符。
So that on the next line we can you just,
所以在下一行里，我们需要一个新的
new uniquely idefy, identify your calculator.
唯一的标识符，标识你的计算器。
So here if your a Stanford student,
所以如果你是斯坦福的学生，
you'll wanna use this reverse DNS notation here edu.stanford.cs1983p.
你可以用这个倒序的域名：edu.stanford.cs1983p 。
And instead of instructor there, you wanna put your SU net ID.'Kay?
并用你的 SU net ID 将 instructor 替换。
Cuz nobody else has that but you.
因为你的ID不会和别人的重复
And that'll uniquely identify you.
这样这个标识符就能作为唯一标识你。
As I said, we're using Swift not Objective-C.
我说过，我们要用 Swift 而不是 Objective-C。
And we're gonna build an app that works be, equally well on iPad and iPhone,
我们要创建的应用要能同时工作在 iPad 和 iPhone上，
that's called a universal app.
所以选择 Universal。
You can pick to develop for only one or the other.
你也可以选择只为其中一种设备开发。
But we are going to go universal here.
但是我们在这里选择 universal。
We're not gonna really be doing the iPad part of it for a couple weeks.
在这几周之内我们不会做这个应用的 iPad 部分。
But it is our intent to eventually build an app that works on both.
但是我们最终会把它设计成一个同时能够运行在 iPad 和 iPhone 上的应用。
Okay we're not going to be using Core Data,
我们现在还用不到 Core Data。
that's object oriented database stuff so you just leave that unchecked.
那是关于面向对象的数据库，现在先不要选它。
And now it's asking where we want to save it, I strongly recommend saving in your
现在，它问我们要把项目保存在哪里，我强烈建议保存在你的
home directory, this is my home directory here in a folder called Developer, okay?
home 目录下，这是我的 home 目录，里面有一个 Developer 的目录，看到没？
You could put other folders in here if you want to arrange it more,
当然你也可以在这里放其它文件夹，如果你想创建更多的话
but home directory Developer, I highly recommend that.
不过我建议你放在主目录下的Developer文件夹
Source control, we will be talking about that at some point in the quarter but
Source control，我们将会在这学期的某些时候讲到，不过
we're not gonna do it right off the bat here so
我们先跳过这个
you can leave that unchecked as well.
所以那个选项你可以不打勾
All right, so here's our first project, its been created so
好啦，这就是我们创建的第一个项目
this is Xcode that your seeing right here, this is Xcode's main screen and
这里你看到的就是 Xcode, 这是 Xcode 的主窗口
the center is really what your working on.
中间这部分是主要的工作区域
The left is, area here, is called the navigator, and the navigator you,
左边的区域，被称作 navigator（导航栏）
you use to kind of choose what you're working on but you can also do
通常用来选择特定的选项，不过也你可以
things over here like search hough your whole project, that's this little guy.
点击这个小图标，对整个项目进行搜索
Look at all your break points maybe, look at previous builds that you've done,
这里用来查看断点，这里用来查看之前编译的项目
browse your project by class hierarchy, all that stuff.
这里可以以类的层次结构展开整个项目，等等
But we're usually on the left most one here which is just all of the files in
不过我们通常会点击最左边的这里，这里可以看到我们所有的文件
your project which can also can be organized hierarchically like this.
你的项目可以像这样按层次的展现出来
And when you select something here on the left,
当你选择左边区域这里的某些部分，
the middle will fill up with what that you've selected so.
中间区域会出现你刚刚选择的那部分内容
Here I have the actual project itself selected.
这里我选择了这个项目本身
So these are the project settings of which there are tons.
所以这里可以看到这个项目的很多设置项
All along the top here you can see tons of settings.
在这上面你还可以看到更多设置项
We're, we'll go through them as the quarter goes on and
随着学期进展我们将会讲到这些
you've already seen some of them like the bundle identifier there and
你已经看到其中的一部分，比如这里的 Bundle identifier（包标识符）
the fact this is a universal app.
还可以看到这里是一个通用 app
We're not going to talk about anymore of this today,
不过我们今天不会讲关于项目设置
this project settings business.
的更多内容
We're gonna focus here on some of these files.
我们会把注意力集中在这些文件
And even some of these files, like this AppDelegate,
甚至是这些文件，比如 AppDelegate
I'm just gonna move that down to Supporting Files to get it out of the way.
我会把它们移到 Supporting Files
Same things with these image assets,
image assets 文件夹也是
LaunchScreen well get to this later in the quarter.
LaunchScreen 我们之后会讲到
But I wanna focus on these two files right here.
不过我们现在会把注意力集中在这两个文件上
Okay Main.storyboard and ViewController.swift, okay
Main.storyboard 和 ViewController.swift
In the MVC world by the way, this is the V,
顺便说，在 MVC 中这称为 V
the view and this is the C, the controller but we will talk about MVC on Wednesday.
即视图，这是 C，即控制器，我们将在周三讲到 MVC
So what do these things contain?
所以，这些东西包含什么
So this Main.storyboard, if I click on it,
这是 Main.storyboard，如果我点击它
you see it appear in the middle, this is our UI.
可以看到我们的 UI 出现在中间
Okay, this is our user interface.
恩，这就是我们的用户界面
So for a calculator this is going to be a little display,
对于计算器而言，这里将会是一个稍微小一点的显示区域
this shows the number that we're working on or whatever at the top.
这里会显示我们计算出来的数字或任何其它在上面的数字
And lots of buttons down here, number buttons, times, multi, or sorry, times,
下面这里会有很多按钮，包括数字，乘除
divide, plus, minus, square root.
加减，平方根
That's all going to be here.
都会出现在这里
So we're going to build this entire user interface.
所以我们即将完全图形化地搭建
Purely graphically.
整个用户界面
Okay? We're not gonna be writing code.
我们不会写代码
Put button at this location.
来指出哪个按钮该放哪个位置
None of that, okay?
一点代码都没有。
We just literally with our mouse are gonna build this whole user interface.
我们只是用我们的鼠标来搭建我们的用户界面
So what's the code, what do we need any code for?
那我们的代码写在哪里，什么时候需要写代码？
Well, we, this ViewController.swift, this is a Swift file.
看 ViewController.swif，这个 Swift 文件
This is your first look at Swift for most of you.
这是你们中多数人第一次看 Swift 文件
This controller is gonna control that user interface.
这是我们的控制器，用来控制我们的用户界面
That's why we call it the view controller or the controller.
这就是为什么我们称之为视图控制器或控制器
It controls user interface and that means it's gonna do things that
它控制用户界面，这意味着它会做某些事情来
are specific to how this user interface, a calculator's user interface, works.
比如指定这个用户界面，计算器界面应该怎样工作
So when we press the digit buttons, it's going to have update the display.
这样当你点击数字按钮，它会更新显示的内容
When we press times, it's gonna have to do some multiplication and
当我们点击乘法，它将会进行乘法运算并且
then put the result in the display.
把结果显示出来
So it's controlling the display.
所以说它会控制界面的展示
Okay so we'll get back to this code in a moment but we're gonna start by
我们稍后再回到这里，现在我们先从搭建界面开始
building our user interface and by the way, your user interface, you can see I
顺便说一句，你可以看到这个用户界面
have a low resolution screen here so my UI doesn't even really fit in the space here.
因为屏幕的低分辨率，所以我的UI没有很好地适应空间
You'll probably have maybe a little higher resolution screen then I do but
你们可能有比我更高的屏幕分辨率的屏幕
if you don't, you can zoom in and out, I'm just right-clicking,
不过如果你们没有，你们可以通过右键点击来进行放大和缩小
if you right-click on the background area here, you can zoom in and out.
如果你在这个背景区域点击右键，你可以放大缩小
You can also do it by double-clicking so if I double-click on this,
你也可以采用双击，看如果我双击这里
it zooms it to normal, if I double-click on the background, it zooms out so
它放大到正常水平，如果我再双击背景，它会缩小
that way I can see my whole UI.
这样我可以看到我的整个 UI 界面
Now when we build a complicated app
当我们完成了一个复杂的 app
we're gonna have a whole bunch of these little square areas, we call these scenes,
我们将会有一大堆这些方块区域，这些我们称之为 scenes（场景）
and a scene represents kind of phone full, phone screen full of information.
一个场景代表一个完整显示所有信息的手机屏幕
Okay and as you you've used many iOS applications, you know that you
就像你使用过的许多 iOS 程序
transition from one screen to another as the user goes through the app and
你知道用户使用这个 app 从一个屏幕切换到另外一个屏幕
that's how your gonna build your apps as well.
这也是你搭建 app 的方式
And this storyboard is eventually gonna have a big map showing all
这个 storyboard 最终将会有一个大的地图来显示所有的
the transitions between all those scenes.
场景间的切换
Okay, so this storyboard is gonna get big for
好了，所以这个 storyboard 将会用来搭建
big apps, your really gonna see your whole application which is kinda cool.
完整的 app，所以当你真的看到整个应用程序时，还挺酷的
So we're gonna start small though, just this one little screen right here.
所以我们将从这一个小的场景开始
Which is gonna be our calculator.
搭建我们的计算器
So let's start building our calculator with it's display.
我们先从搭建计算器的界面显示开始
So I wanna make a display.
所以，当我想显示一些东西时，
So how do I do that?
我应该怎么做呢？
Well that brings us to the right side, the right-hand side here,
我们看一下这里的右边区域
this whole right side, this is called the Utilities area
右边的整块区域，我们称为工具区域
You can see that's it's got a bottom and a top, right?
你可以看到这里有底部和顶部，对不？
We want to go into the bottom and on the third tab right here, which is called
来到底部这里的第三个按钮，它被我们称为
the Object Library, you'll see that there's tons and tons of objects in here.
对象库，你可你看到这里有非常多的对象
Okay, dozens of these things and
非常多的这类东西
we're gonna get to a lot of these by the end of the quarter.
我们整个学期会接触到很多这样的东西
But these are the things you build your user interface out of.
这些是用于搭建你的用户界面的
So kind of towards the top, not all the way at the top, but towards the top,
靠近上面，但不完全靠近上面，就在这上面
you'll start seeing things like buttons and text fields and things like that.
你会开始看到像按钮，文本区域这样的东西
Well this is what we need obviously, to build our display here,
很明显这是我们构建显示区域所需要的东西
is some sort of text field, and there's a couple of them here.
是某种显示文本的区域，这里有两种
One, this one called Label is static text, you see?
这一种称为 Label 的是一种静态的文本，看到不？
And this one Text Field is editable text, in other words you can touch on this one.
这种称为 Text Field 是一张可编辑的文本，也就是说，你当你按下时
And the little keyboard would slide up from the bottom and you could type in it.
键盘会从底部滑出来，所以你可以输入文本
So, the calculator, you can't really touch on the screen and
因此对于计算器来说，你确实不能按下屏幕并且
start typing so we want this static text.
输入，所以我们需要固定的文本
So, I'm just going to pick this up with the mouse and drag it out.
所以我用我的鼠标把它拖出来
Now, when I drag it out into my UI,
现在，当我把它拖入我的UI中时
you're going to see a lot of little blue dash lines appearing.
你会看到很多蓝色虚线出现，
You see these?
看到没
These are helping me put this in the right place.
这些可以帮助我们正确地摆放这些东西
So, I can put it right in the center, for example, of my view.
所以，比如说我可以把它放在视图的中间
I could put it up in a corner up here, which is what I'm gonna do.
我可以把它放在靠顶部这里，我待会就准备这样做
Mm-kay.
You always want your things that you put in your UI,
你总是会希望你放入UI中的东西
as much as humanly possible, to be on one of these dashed blue lines.
尽可能地去利用这些蓝色虚线
And you'll understand why in a couple weeks when we
你会明白为什么几周之后当我们
starting talking about auto-layout.
开始关于auto-layou（自动布局）的课程
I'm gonna do a little auto-layout right here just to kind of
我这里将会涉及一点关于auto-layou的东西，可以让你
give you a feel for it.
它有点感觉
But those blue, dashed blue lines are gonna be your best friend when it comes to
不过，在你搭建用户界面的时候，这些蓝色虚线将会是你最好的朋友
building your user interface and you'll quickly see why that is.
你会很快知道为什么了
Once you drag something out like this, you can,
每次你像这样拖动东西，你可以
these little things are rounded that show it's selected, right?
看到环绕在外面的东西，它表明了这个被选中了
They also are little resize handles so you can grab them and resize them when you
它们也可以用于调整大小，所以可以抓住它然后或者重新调整它们的大小
resize it also re-puts those dashed blue lines out there, okay?
当你调整大小时，这些蓝色虚线会重新排成一列，看到没
So you definitely wanna, even have,
所以当你调整大小时，你肯定想
when you're resizing, get those things lining up.
把这些东西排成一列
You can also manipulate it directly, just double-click on it, like a calculator
你还可以操作这些东西，只需要双击一下
probably doesn't want to come up, this is gonna be initial state of this.
通常计算器的初始状态不是这样子
Doesn't want to come up saying Label, it probably wants 0 or
初始状态上面不会显示Label，它可能会显示0
something like that in it's display.
或类似的东西
There's also things you wanna set about this though or
还有另外一张方式，当你无法正确地设置这种
anything you drag in your UI that you just can't direct manipulate and
拖入你UI的任何东西时
that's what the top half of this Utilities windows is, is for, okay?
你可以使用靠上的Utilities windows（工具窗口）
So if you look at the top half here,
所以当你看上面这里
there's a bunch of tabs across the top including something like this,
在顶部这里有许多标签，包括像这种
the Size Inspector for setting the size of this thing.
用于设置尺寸的Size Inspector（尺寸调节器）
And this tab right here, really important, this is the Attributes Inspector.
还有这里的这个标签，称作Attributes Inspector（属性检查器），非常重要
And this is an object oriented inspector, depending on what you have selected.
这是一个面向对象的检查器，当你选择不同的东西时
You'll have different user interface here in the top.
用户界面将会有所改变
And this let's you edit attributes about what's selected.
这个可以让你编辑你选中的东西的属性
So, for example,
比如
a calculator, the zero doesn't really want to be on the left, right?
计算器中这个0其实不是在左边，对不
Calculators, the zero, the numbers are on the right and
这个0应该是在右边
they kind of grow out from the right.
这些数字就像是从右边出现的
And so we can easily fix that with this alignment thing right here.
所以我们可以很轻松地使用这里的alignment（校准）修改它
So I'm gonna click this and you see the zero move over to the right.
我点击这里所以你可以看到0移动到右边
And, and maybe I want a bigger font.
还有，也许我想要大点的字体
You see the font right here.
你可以看到这里的font（字体）
I can click on this, pick different fonts.
我可以点击这里，选择不同的字体
I'm gonna just move it up to like 32 point, it's a nice big font.
把它增大到32点，稍微大点的字体
You can notice it kinda cuts off.
你可以看到字体有点被截小了
I made it so big that it's too small.
字体放大因此这里显得太小
So I can always just resize this larger to make that fit.
所以我可以重新调整大小使之适应字体的大小
So this is how we build our user interface.
这就是我们搭建用户界面的方式
It's very direct manipulation and very object oriented as you'll start to
非常直观的操作，并且非常地面向对象
see when we add different kinds of objects.
当你加入不同的对象时你就可以看到
So, let's actually run this application, okay?
所以，让我们真正地运行我们的应用
We haven't done, built any calculaterness about it, but
我们还没有完成，任何关于计算的东西
we have this one field, let's run it and see what it looks like.
不过让我们运行一下看看是上面效果
So, how do you run things?
所以，应该如何运行？
Well, you see right here where it says, iPhone 6?
嗯，这里你可以看到，iPhone 6？
This actually is a selector that lets you say where you want to
这实际上是可以让你选择在哪里
run your application.
运行你的应用
So you can see you can run it on an iOS device if you have one connected,
所以你有一个iOS设备连接上时，你可以运行在iOS设备上
I don't have one connected
currently.
现在我还没有连接的设备
But you can do that.
不过你可以选择那个选项
And we'll talk in a Friday section probably in a week or
我们将会在一到两周后的周五
two about how to get your devices hooked up.
谈论如何连接你的设备
But also there's these plethora of simulators here, iPhone 6,
不过这里有很多模拟器iPhone 6
6+, iPhone 5, iPhone 4s, iPad Airs.
6+, iPhone 5, iPhone 4s, iPad Airs
And you can pick one of these to run on and
你可以选择其中的一个运行
it'll actually simulate that device right here on your computer.
它实际上是在你的电脑上模拟那些设备
So I'm gonna run on the iPhone 6.
所以我将会运行在iPhone 6
Okay,I'm just gonna hit Play, see this Play button right here?
好了，我将要点击Play按钮，看到Play按钮没
That's how you simulate, so Play.
这就是使用模拟器的方式，所以点击Play
Now it's launching the simulator.
现在启动模拟器
It's a separate process.
它是一个独立的处理进程
And it's going to run our app in there.
将会在这里运行我们的app
And there it is.
情况就是这样
Now you might say, whoop.
现在你可能会说，哇
Big white square.
这么大的白色正方形
Oh that's not so good.
看起来不怎么好
And the reason this is so
这是因为
big is because the iPhone 6 has a very high resolution display on it.
iPhone 6的高分辨率屏幕
Okay, the retina display, and it's way higher resolution than my computer, okay?
视网膜屏幕，比我电脑上的分辨率大得多
So I actually have to scroll around, you see there's the top of it.
所以我实际上不得不进行滑动，你可以看到它的顶部
Scroll up and down to get to i all.
通过上下滑动可以看到整个区域
Luckily if you go to Window, this is not in the simulator now, the iOS simulator.
幸运的是如果我们前往Window选项，这个选项现在不在iOS模拟器
If you go to Window and Scale, you can scale it down to be smaller and
如果你点击Window并且点击Scale，你可以把它缩得更小
then it'll fit.
使之适用屏幕
Okay, so if you have a low resolution screen,
因此，如果你有低分辨率的屏幕
you're definitely gonna wanna use Window > Scale.
你肯定会点击Window > Scale
Cmd+3 right there is another way to do it.
快捷键Cmd+3是另外一种方式
Okay?
懂不
So here's our UI, but it doesn't look to good, okay, because where's this?
所以，这就是我们的UI，不过看起来不怎么样，因为这个在哪？
We put this zero in there and it just never showed up, what did we do wrong?
我们把0放在这里然后它从来都没有出现，我们哪里做错了？
Well we didn't really do anything wrong and that zero is actually there.
实际上我们没有做错，那个0实际上就在那里
It's just, here let me line up these UI's, this is not
它只是，先让我把UI排成一列，虽然没有
necessarily exactly the same scale but its appropriate, approximately the same scale,
必要完全相同的缩放尺寸，不过刚好是同样的尺寸
you can see that the zero is actually off screen, [NOISE] okay?
你可以看到那个0实际上在屏幕外面，看到不？
So its there but you just can't see it because its over here off the screen.
所以实际上它存在只不过你没有看到它，因为它在屏幕外面
Okay, and that's a problem, but that's a problem we can fix.
这是一个问题，不过这个问题我们可以解决
So let's go fix that problem.
所以我们开始解决这个问题
Why is that thing off-screen?
为什么它在屏幕外面？
Well, look at this UI right here, okay?
好了，看到这个UI没
What shape is it?
它是什么形状的？
It's square.
它是正方形的
Okay, no IOS device is square.
不过没有任何iOS设备是正方形的
There's not a single square iOS device in the world.
世界上没有任何一种正方形的iOS设备
They're all, you know, tall and
你知道的，它们都是高的，并且
thin, or, if you turn them sideways, then they're long and short.
瘦的，或者如果把它们侧身来看，它们都又长又短
Or even like an iPad.
甚至像一个iPad
You know the aspect ratio on an iPad is slightly different than an iPhone so
你知道iPad的纵横比和iPhone稍微有点不同
their all slightly different, but none of\ them are square.
它们略有不同，但他们都不是正方形的
So why do we design our UI in a square?
所以为什么我们把我们的UI设计为方的？
Because the way you design iOS interfaces, you design them in this square and
因为你设计iOS界面的方式是你把它们设计在这个方形中并且
you give everything inside the square rules, called constraints,
你给所有东西添加这些规则，这些规则我们称之为约束
about what happens to them when they get squished down.
是关于当它们被压扁时应该发生什么事情
Either squished down vertically, squished down horizontally,
不过是水平还是垂直的压扁
depending on what kinda device their getting put on, okay?
取决于它们被放到哪种设备中，明白不
So you put these rules in there, so, what does it look like to put these rules in?
所以你会在加入这些规则，所以当加入这样规则后看起来会怎样？
Well again, it's all direct manipulation, so
同样的，这些都是直观的操作
I'm going to give some rules to this label right here to make it so that it knows
我将要对这里的这个标签增加一些规则，使得它知道
what to do when this square gets squished down in any direction for any device.
对于任何方向的任何设备被压扁时应该如何显示
So, what do I want the rules to be?
所以，我希望这些规则是什么样的？
Well, I always want this thing to use the whole width.
我总希望它可以使用全部的宽度
However much width I have, I want it all.
不管我的宽度是多少，我都希望填满这个宽度
So I'm gonna pin this right edge to this edge, okay?
所以我要固定这个右边缘到这个边缘的距离，ok？
I'm gonna make it so all widths are pinned to each other.
我这样做是因为所有宽度都会由另外一方决定
And I do that with the Ctrl key.
我使用Ctrl键来完成
I've turned on sticky keys so
我已经开启粘滞键所以
you can see down in the lower left here, it's showing the modifier keys I'm using.
在左下角你可以看到，它显示了我正使用的修饰键
So right now I'm holding down Ctrl.
所以现在我按住Ctrl
And I'm gonna Ctrl+drag from the right edge of this to the container it's in.
我会按Ctrl 从右边拖动到它的容器的右边
See how it's showing me what I'm dragged to.
看它是如何展示我正在拖动的过程
So when I drag to this container, it puts a menu up and says,
所以，当我拖到这个容器时，它会出现菜单并且提示我
oh, okay, you want some rule between that label's right edge and
好吧，你想在标签和右边缘之间增加一些规则
this thing's edge, what do you want it to be?
这个边缘，你希望是什么情况？
Well, I can do a lot of things here.
恩，我可以在这上面做很多事情
I could center this label vertically in this container.
我可以使这个标签垂直居中于这个容器
Up, you know, vertical up and down.
向上，你知道的，垂直向上和向下
I definitely don't want that, I want my label at the top, so I don't want that.
我绝对不希望出现这种情况，我希望我的标签在顶部，所以我不希望出现这种情况
I can make it the equal width, so
我可以使它的宽度相等，所以
I can make this label the same width as the container.
我可以使这个标签和这个容器中宽度相同
I don't want that either, cuz I want this little margin there, right?
我也不想那种情况，因为我想设置这个小边距，对不对？
But look at the top one, trailing space to container margin.
不过看上面的那个，trailing space to container margin（距离容器的间距）
This lets me pin the trailing space after my label to the margin of the container.
这让我规定了我的标签和它的容器的间距
So that's the one I want, so I'm gonna click on this and it does it.
所以这就是我希望的那个，所以我点击这个
Now, see all these yellow and orange lines that appeared when I did that?
现在，当我这样做时，看到这些黄色和橙色的线条出现没？
That's because the systems like, okay, you've started telling me the rules for
这就像是系统在说，OK，你已经开始告诉我应该遵循关于这些标签的某些规则
this label, but your you haven't told me enough rules,
不过你没有告诉我足够多的规则
I don't know what to do with this thing.
我不知道应该对它怎么做
So now it's showing you all the places where it's like the system's not
所以它现在正在告诉你，当它被挤压的时候
sure what to do now when this thing gets squished.
系统不确定应该怎么做
Before it was like, okay, well you weren't telling me anything so
在这之前，你没有告诉我任何规则
I'm not going to do anything, but now your starting to tell me.
所以我没有显示任何东西，不过现在你开始告诉我
So what do I do?
所以我应该怎么做？
So we have to fully specify both the what happens horizontally and
所以我们不得不完整地告诉它水平方向
vertically to this thing.
和垂直方向应该怎么显示
So we've only just started here.
所以我们仅仅先从这里开始
So let's pin this edge also cuz we want this edge to stay on this side.
所以让我们拖动固定这个边缘，我们希望这个边缘靠近这一边
So I'm gonna hold down Ctrl and drag.
所以我按下Ctrl并且拖动
And now I'm gonna pin the leading space to the container margin.
然后现在我想固定它到容器之间的间距
Okay, boom that did that.
好了，我成功了
Still have orange going on here, that's because I haven't specified anything about
这里仍然显示橙色，这是因为我还没指定任何关于
the vertical position of this label so I'm gonna pin the top to the top, so
这个标签的垂直位置，所以我把顶部和顶部固定起来
hold Ctrl again, drag up here, this is now top space.
所以我有一次按住Ctrl，拖到这里，这是顶部间距
Notice that it realizes where I am dragging to and from, right?
注意到它识别出我正把它拖向哪里没？
So they can give me options that make sense,
所以它能给我有意义的选项
like Top Space to Layout Guide here.
比如这里的Top Space to Layout Guide(顶部间距)
So I'm going to do that.
所以我会选这个
So now I'm starting to get blue lines.
所以我开始看到蓝色的线了
You see these lines?
看到没
I hope you can see that there.
希望你能看到
They're solid blue, not orange or red.
它们是实心蓝线，不是橙色或红色
Okay, that's because they're okay, we are okay horizontally here.
这是因为它们ok了，水平方向上ok了
But we still have a problem vertically.
不过这里仍然有一个垂直方向上的问题
Now I'm not sure exactly what the problem is vertically cuz I really don't
现在我不是非常确定这个垂直方向上的问题因为我确实不
want the bottom of this.
希望这样的底部
I just want it to hang out wherever it wants to hang out based on the size of my
希望我这个刚刚摆放的标签的底部是基于我的
font or whatever.
字体大小
So I don't, I don't really wanna specify anything here so
因此，我不，我确实不想在这里指明特定的高度
why is this orange and how do I get rid of this?
所以为什么橙色警告会出现，我应该怎样避免它？
Well any time you have orange and when you're doing this layout stuff and
任何时候当你在布局时看到橙色警告
you don't know what to do.
你不知道应该怎样做
You wanna go down to this button right here, okay?
你会来到下面这里点击这个按钮，看到不？
This is the document outline.
这是document outline（文档大纲)
And when you click this, a little thing will slide out, a little shelf here.
当你点击这里时，这一小部分会滑出来，一个小架子
And this is an outline view of everything that's in your UI.
这是你的UI中所有东西的大纲
Okay? And they're linked, so
并且它们之间已经连接起来
if I click the background, nothing is selected.
如果我点击背景，什么都没有被选中
Then the background, the view is what's selected here.
然后这个背景，这个视图就是我这里选择的
But if I click this L0, which means a label with zero in it,
但当我点击这里L0标签时，L0指的是Label中显示内容是0
look it's selected my.
看我的标签被
Zero label, and vice versa if I click on this here, it selects it over here.
选中，反之亦然如果我点击这里，这里显示被选中
So this is this same thing in an outline mode.
所以这和大纲模式一样
This is really nice to have.
这是一种非常好的方式
Sometimes you have views that are overlapping and they're kind of in
有时候你的视图重叠在一起，所以它们显得有点
each other's way, you can always go here to select the one you want, okay?
难以选择，你可以来到这里选择你想选择的视图，ok？
And you can Ctrl+drag to these over here too it's just as much Ctrl+draggable as
并且你也可以在这里Ctrl加拖动，这里和其它东西
some of these other things.
一样可Ctrl+拖动
But what we're, and we'll look,
但这些我们将会
we'll talk about top layout
guide, bottom
layout guide a little later.
稍后我们将讨论一下顶部和底部的布局指南。
But what I really want you to
focus on is
this little yellow circle up
here.
但是我想让你注意这个黄色的小圆圈
'Kay?
Any time you got yellow and
好的，任何时候，你都会在使用auto-Layout中看到黄色和橙色的警告
orange problems with this
auto-layout
business,
you're gonna get this little
yellow circle
appearing in your document
outline.
你可以在你的左侧文档中看到这个小黄圈出现。
And if you click it, it'll slide
in a list
of all the problems.
如果你点击它，它会展开一个列表，呈现所有的问题
And so here I highlight over
this and this
is where all the orange and
yellow is.
如果选中它，出现高亮的部分就是警告所出现的地方
It's saying the label with the 0
in it
expected the height to be 39 but
它提示这个label的高度应该是39，但
the actual height is 57.
真实的情况却是57。
Well that's because after I set
this font,
这是因为我在设置了这个字体后，
I just dragged this down a
little bit to
make space.
我向下的拖动了一部分，让它多出来一些区域。
All right, I, I wasn't very, I,
I didn't
know it was supposed to be 39.
好吧，我不是很，我不是很清楚它支持的高度是39。
I just dragged down.
我只是稍稍向下拖动了而已。
And so it's saying that's wrong.
这样，Xcode给了我一个警告。
Now, I could just try drag it
back up and
meet this dashed line.
现在,我可以试着将其拖动，和这个虚线重叠。
This dashed line, by the way,
强调下这条虚线，
is where it's kind of saying,
this is
really where this thing wants to
be.
它表明了这个标签真实的大小。
But the solid lines are where it
actually
is.
但是实线是我们希望的样子。
So I could kinda drag it up to
there, but
I, I could be off by a pixel or
所以我可能拖动到那里，但是我也许会相差1个像素或
something else.
出现一些其他的区别。
A much more reliable way is to
click this
little yellow triangle, 'kay?
现在有一个可靠的方法，点击这个黄色小三角，好了吗？
So I'm gonna click this yellow
triangle.
我将要点击这个。
It's gonna bring up this pop-up
window.
它会弹出一个窗口。
And there's three ways to fix
the
problems, okay?
这里给出了三个修改问题的方法，好了吗同学？
One way, Update Constraints,
this middle
way right here.
其中一个，更新约束，在第二个。
That's a way that says, hey, I
want this
thing to be,
这个方法是，我想要这样做，
this label to be right where it
is.
这个label这样才是正确的。
So just make some constraints.
所以只要做一些约束。
Make it up.
弥补上这个缺点。
Make it happen!
让它自己完成。
And it'll put some wacky
constraints in
there like 52 high, which is a
bad
它会把一些古怪的约束添加到这个52高度，这是一个坏的
constraint for it to be, 52
high, cuz this
label wants to be its natural
height.
约束，因为52的高度不是这个标签真正的高度。
It doesn't want to be 52 high.
它的高度不是52。
So this'll kinda force
constraint.
所以这里就可以用强制性的约束。
You'll almost never want this
one, 'kay.
当然你也许不希望这样。
Rarely do you wanna force the
constraints.
你很少想强制性的去约束。
Reset to Suggested Constraints
would
probably just work here.
这个就是设置label为建议性的约束。
I'm not gonna choose this one,
but it
would probably work.
我不会选择这个，即使它可能是正确的。
This one is going to make the
constraints
match the blue lines.
这个是将约束调整为蓝色的线条。
Those dashed blue lines that I
told you
always wanna meet.
那些蓝线，我告诉你是必须达到的。
Those are what's gonna help the
system
pick suggested constraints.
那些是系统帮助选择出来的约束。
So since we dragged that label
out to the
blue lines perfectly,
因为我们拖动的label是蓝色的，
I'll bet if I said Reset to
Suggested
Constraints, it might just work.
我敢打赌，我点击了重置约束，它也是能够工作的。
Okay.
But I'm actually gonna show you
this
好的。我想告诉你这个
last option up on top, which is
Update
Frame and what this says is,
take into
选项，它是能够更新框架和
consideration all the rules and
move this
label to where the rules say it
should be.
所有的约束规则，让label的按照规则进行移动。
'Kay.
And I like this option a lot
because it
好的，我喜欢这个选项
lets you kind of preview, do I
have my
little rules right, okay?
它让你能够预览，我有一个正确的结果，对吗？
So let's try that, let's see if
the, we'll
tell the, move this label, go
ahead and
我们尝试一下，看下移动后的标签是
move yourself and size yourself
to obey
these three rules we you put in,
and
遵守你自己的设定的那三个约束，
we'll fix the misplacement, so
let's try
it.
我们点击这个按钮，让我们尝试下。
And sure enough it did it, it
says there
are no auto layout issues.
果然做到了，没有任何问题。
If I go back to my document
outline, this
little yellow circle is gone.
如果你回到自己的目录列表，这个黄色的小圆圈已经消失了。
If I look in my view, everything
is
blue-lined, no yellow or red.
看看自己的视图，全部都是蓝线，没有红色或黄色的。
Okay?
So that's your
好了吗？这就说明你的
crash course on auto layout, and
we're
gonna talk a lot more about auto
layout,
自动布局已经完成，我们接下来讨论下更多的自动布局
in fact, even on Wednesday I'm
gonna do
another auto layout with all the
buttons.
在周三的时候我们将要尝试给所有的按钮进行自动布局。
Right?
The keypad buttons, and
真的？所有的键盘按钮
all that, which is a lot more
things being
laid out.
这听起来真的蛮多的。
But let's see if this fixes our
problem.
接着让我们看下如何修改这些。
Let's go ahead and run our
application
again.
我们再次运行一下应用。
So I'm just hitting that play
button.
点击这个运行按钮。
Here it, oh, we got our zero
this time.
此刻，我们现在可以看到这个0了。
You see how it pinned this zero
to that
edge?
你注意到这个零的边缘了吗?
And not only that, if we rotate
this
phoned,
不仅可以这样，如果我们旋转模拟器，
which you can do in the
Simulators menu,
Hardware > Rotate.
你可以在模拟器的菜单中点击Hardware>Rotate。
Look the 0, this got wider and
the 0 kept
pin, pinning itself over to
that.
看看这个0，它本身还保持着这个距离。
And it also stayed on the top
even though
this got, whole thing got
shorter.
它也保持着距离顶部的距离，底部距离变短了。
Okay.
And if I rotate back, the 0
stays there.
接下来，如果我旋转回来，0还是保持原样。
Question.
So what did it do at the bottom
there?
学生提问：是什么让它底部产生了变化。
Like what did the actual update
frame end
up doing?
就像你已经更新过那里的约束了一样。
What did the update frame in the
document
outline do?
在目录中的更新框架做了什么呢？
Yes.
It moved this bottom edge up.
是的，它改变了底部的边缘距离。
You see this is only 39 pixels
high now.
你看现在是39的像素高度。
It was 52.
之前它是52.
So, yeah, it just moved it up.
这样，它发生了改变，向上移动了。
It, it, and if other things had
been
yellow,
如果其他事情提示黄色，
it could have moved the whole
thing.
它可能移动整体了。
Right?
It would move that
好的，它将移动这
whole rectangle wherever the
rule said but
整个矩形达到约束的那样，但是
in this case, you can fi that
one problem
by moving it up.
这种情况，你能够向上拖动来修改这个问题。
Good question.
好问题。
Okay?
可以了嘛？
So that's good.
不错。
All right.
好的。
So that's it for auto layout.
让我们回到自动布局上。
Auto layout part one.
自动布局的第一部分。
So now let's talk a little bit
about
connecting our user interface
that we're
所以现在让我们来谈谈我们的界面,我们
building right here, up to the
code,
建立在这里，通过代码
cuz we want that code to be able
to talk
to the user interface.
因为我们想让代码能够告诉用户界面。
Otherwise how are we gonna have
the number
buttons,
否则我们如何拥有数字按钮，
make numbers appear up here in
the
display?
使数字展现在这里
Or the times button, give the
results of
the calculation up here.
或一些按钮，告诉计算结果在这里。
We gotta be able to talk to
this.
我们必须能够与之交互。
So how do we do that?
但是如何做到呢？
And the answer, first step is,
we need to
get both this co, this Swift
Code,
正确答案，第一步需要我们在controller中编写Swift代码，
the controller, and this view on
screen at
the same time, 'kay?
和这个视图相互对应。
Cuz we're gonna connect them so
we need
them on screen at the same time,
因为我们会连接他们,所以我们需要在屏幕上在同一时间
and there's a lot of ways to do
that, but
I'll do the simplest way right
here,
还有很多方面,在这里我要用最简单的方法,
which is this little button
called the
assistant editor, all right?
这个小按钮叫助理编辑，好了吗？
So I'm gonna click that and
look!
我要点击这个。
It put them both on screen at
the same
time, exactly what I wanted.
这时你能看到屏幕分成了两部分，这正是我想要的。
Now it's all a little crowded
here.
现在它这里是比较拥挤的。
Even if I expand my view a
little bit,
it's like it's all smashed in
here.
即使我放大整个界面，它看起来还是这么小。
Luckily the navigator and the
utilities
can also be hidden,
幸运的是导航栏这些都是可以隐藏起来的，
see these buttons up here, these
three
buttons?
看到这些按钮了嘛，这有三个按钮。
This left one, if you click it
hides the
navigator and
左侧这个，如果你点击它则会隐藏左侧导航，
this right one if you click it
hides
utilities, 'kay?
点击右侧这个，则会右侧右边的工具栏。
So now we have both my UI and
over here we
can still double click to zoom
out, but
现在我们可以看到他们都在视线中，我们可以双击缩放它，但
the thing is, anytime we're
actually
connecting our UI to our code or
事情是这样的,在我们实际连接UI代码或
trying to edit anything in here,
you need
to be zoomed to normal, 'kay?
尝试去编辑的时候，你需要把缩放比例调到正常。
For example if I tried to select
if I'm
zoomed out and
例如这个，如果我选择这个比例
I try to select this 0 I just
can't.
我就不能选中这个0了。
This is really kind of a bird's
eye view
just for seeing what your UI
looks like.
这个其实只是一个预览图，让你看看大体样子，而不能编辑。
If you wanna actually work on
it,
你只有这样才能够继续工作，
you double-click to zoom in on
this scene
that you're interested in.
你双击选择这个窗口即可。
Okay, so here's our Swift code.
好了，现在我们开始编写Swift代码。
I'm actually gonna delete these.
我将要删除这些。
We don't need them for the
calculator.
在我们的应用中是不需要这些的。
We will need these things for
future
application but we don't need it
for
我们需要一些计算功能，但这些不需要。
the calculator.
And this is your first look at
Swift,
'kay.
接着，你将要开始第一个Swift的编写。
So Swift, as I said, very
concise
language, but it's basically an
object
我说过，Swift是非常简洁的语言，但它还是一个
oriented language, it's gonna
look a lot
like C, some things look a lot
like Java.
面向对象语言，它看起来像C，有人说它有点像java。
It's kind of the, you know, best
of, of a
lot of different worlds at once.
你知道，最好的，很多不同的地方。
Now this import is just
importing the UI
portion of iOS.
这只是iOS导入UI的一部分。
You usually won't have to
specify import
yourself unless you start
你通常不需要指定导入，除非你开始
using frameworks that are not,
you know,
the base frameworks and we'll
get to that
不使用框架，你知道基础框架和我们将要
probably weeks into the quarter
where you
fi, finally have to do an import
yourself.
使用的一些会需要自己进行导入。
So this how it automatically got
put here
for us.
这里我们看到它自动的为我们添加了。
And so this is really your first
line of
Swift code, 'kay?
在这里要开始你的第一行Swift的代码。
Appropriately, it's a definition
of a
class.
这里是定义了一个类。
Cuz Swift is fundamentally
object-oriented
and here we're defining a class.
因为Swift从根本上来讲是面向对象的，这里是定义的一个类。
So what does the syntax look
like to
define a class?
这里的语法看起来像定义一个类吗？
You got the keyword class.
你看到类这个关键字。
You got the name of the class.
这里是这个类的名称。
Now this name ViewController,
pretty bad
name, [LAUGH].
现在这个名字看起来很糟糕。
Okay, very generic, really they
should
probably be something like
好吧,真的很一般,他们应该是类似
CalculatorViewController,
something
specific to
CalculatorViewController这样的命名
this particular scene that we're
working
on right here, that it's
controlling.
这样看起来就让人清楚他是控制哪里的了。
This is the default name it
gives you.
这是个默认的名字。
I don't want to spend the
valuable demo
time showing how to
我不想花费宝贵的时间去演示如何
rename this cuz unfortunately,
重命名这个，因为
I can't just type a new name
here because
I gotta keep the UI in sync with
it.
我不能在这里输入一个新名字,因为我要保持UI同步。
So I would have to do something
in the UI
as well.
所以我必须做一些事情在UI中。
But, for now, for your first
assignment or
two we're, we'll just
但是现在，你的第一个任务或两个，我们只会
call this ViewController, but
down the
road you're gonna wanna pick
better names.
叫他ViewController，但你最好给他更换一个好的名字。
And of course you're gonna be
building
multiple of
当然你可以创建一个
these scenes in this class in
the same app
in the future, so
新的类在其中，
of course, they'll all have
different
controller names.
他们都有一个不同的名称。
Okay, this :UIViewController,
that's
inheritance, that's its
superclass, okay?
这个UIViewController是告诉我们它的父类是谁。
Swift is single inheritance, so
you can
only inherit from one class.
Swift是一个单继承，你只能让他继承一个类。
It's perfectly fine in Swift not
to
inherit from a class if you
don't want to,
如果你不想这样，它是能够完整的继承一个类，
all right?
But here we have to inherit from
UIViewController cuz we
在这里我们有UIViewController，因为我们
want all this magic that allows
us to
control the UI,
想通过它来控制UI，
like that whole auto layout
business, and
there's a ton of mechanism in
here for
像自动布局功能，这其中有许多的原理
the, the allowing the controller
to
control this UI.
允许控制器来控制这个UI
So obviously we do that so all
ViewControllers, all controllers
of these
很明显，所有viewcontroller,所有控制器
little scenes always inherit
from either
from UIViewController directly
or they
这些小场景总是继承UIViewController或者它们
inherit from a class that
inherits from
UIViewController or up their
chain so.
继承的类的UIViewController或它们的链。
And then inside this curly brace
is simply
all the instance variables and
然后在这个花括号中所有实例变量和
methods in this class, 'kay?
方法在这个类中。
So very simple syntax to define
a class.
定义类的语法是非常简练的。
So let's dive right into making
some
instance variables and methods
so
所以让我们忙于做一些实例变量和方法
you can see what those look
like.
你可以调整下位置。
And I thought we, this was
segued to
because we're going to
我想我们，应该连接这个，因为我们想要这个
say we wanted to connect this UI
to this
code.
UI连接到代码中。
So let's do that.
我们现在就这样做。
Let's connect this label right
here into
this code, and
我们连接这个label到代码中去，
then we're gonna do that by
making an
instance variable.
然后我们会通过一个实例变量。
In Swift we call them
properties.
在Swift中我们叫它属性。
'Kay so if you hear me say
property,
如果你听到我说属性，
I'm basically talking about an
instance
variable.
那我其实就是在说实例变量。
Right?
A variable that is part of the
class.
清楚吗？一个变量是类的一部分。
Every instance of the class gets
its own
copy of it.
类的每个实例都有自己的拷贝。
Hopefully you all know what an
instance
variable is.
希望你都知道什么是一个实例变量。
If you don't, again, this class,
如果你不清楚，再说一次，这是类，
heavy object-oriented, you
should
definitely know that.
面向对象的，你应该清楚。
So I'm gonna make a property
here, an
instance variable,
我将要声明一个属性在这里，也可以说是一个实例变量。
that points to this label, so
that I can
update the label's text, right?
使用指针指向这个lable，这样就我就能够更新这个label的内容了。
I need to be able to talk to
this label,
and the way you do that in iO
eh,
我需要告诉这个label，
in Xcode is you hold down Ctrl,
just like
we did when we were making
在Xcode中，你按住Ctrl，像刚才那样
a connection to the edge, so I'm
holding
down Ctrl and clicking on the
label, but
连接边缘，我保持住点击Ctrl和左键在这个label上，但是
instead of going to the edge,
I'm gonna go
into the code, 'kay?
不是要添加约束，我是想让它到代码中去，
Now this is kinda wacky.
这是有点古怪。
I know a lot of you are like
what?
我知道很多你喜欢什么？
Into the code?
在代码中？
Yeah?
So we're going right into the
code here
and let go and it's gonna say
oh,
现在我们到右边代码中，松开鼠标。
you wanna make a connection
between your
UI and your controller.
你能连接UI和控制器了。
No problem, what kinda
connection you
wanna make?
没问题了，接下来需要做什么？
And we wanna make what's called
an outlet
connection.
我们需要设置outlet连接。
An outlet means an instance
variable or
一个outlet在实例变量或
property that points to this
thing in the
UI.
属性，这个指针指向UI。
And all it needs to know to do
that is,
what do you wanna call this
property?
接着你需要给这个属性一个名称。
And this is the display of my
calculator
so I'm gonna call this display
and it
它将出现在我的计算器，所以我将命名为了display，
already knows the type of the
thing is UI
label of course cuz we dragged
from here.
这是说它是什么类型的，因为我们是从这里拖出来的。
Don't worry about this weak,
I'll talk
about that in a moment.
不要担心这个弱连接，在后面我们会讲到。
And then we just hit Connect,
and it
creates an instance variable or
然后我们点击这个按钮,它会创建一个实例变量或
property, right here in our
controller.
称之为属性，完成后就出现在这里了。
So this is a great opportunity
to look at
the syntax in Swift for
在Swift中这个语法就是
creating a property.
创建一个属性。
And there's a couple of things
on here
that are not normally part of
it.
这里有几件事情通常都不是它的一部分。
This is you, the main syntax for
creating
a property.
这是你的主要语法创建一个属性。
Let's quickly look at this thing
to get it
out of the way.
我们快速的了解下这个get方法。
This is not really part of the
Swift
language proper.
这不是Swift真正语言的一部分。
This is something Xcode puts in
here so
这是Xcode将在这里
that this little circle, do you
see the
little circle in this gutter,
appears?
这个小圆圈，你可以看到这个小圆圈出现在这里。
This little circle when I mouse
over it,
look what Xcode does.
当我把鼠标移动到上面时候，看看Xcode的变化。
It shows me what this line of
code is
connected to.
它展示了我选中的代码所连接的UI。
'Kay?
So that's really cool, and
这看起来非常酷，
you're gonna see that's really
valuable
later in this demo,
在这个demo中这是非常有用的，
is being able to find out what
things are
connected to.
它能找到我们连接的是什么控件。
So that's all this thing means
here.
这个就是它所展示的意义。
You, you, you don't type this in
yourself,
that when you Ctrl+drag, it puts
it there.
当你Ctrl+点击拖动时候你不清楚是什么类型，它所说的。
This weak, all you, you, if you
come from
other languages,
这个weak，如果你从其他语言过来到。
you're used to things like
garbage
collection to clean up the heap.
你会使用过类似的垃圾回收机制。
Or maybe you even have to alloc
and
或者你也许习惯自己分配和
free things yourself manually in
some
languages.
释放管理在一些语言中。
None of that in Swift.
在Swift中是没有的。
In Swift, the, all objects live
in the
heap, 'kay.
在Swift中，所有的对象都在堆中。
All class, the instances of
classes live
in the heap.
所有类，类的实例都存在类的堆中。
And the memory for them is
managed for
you, 'kay?
替你进行了内存管理。
You allocate them as much as you
want, as
soon as there's no pointers to
them,
你分配他们尽可能多的你想要的，只要没有了指针指向它们，
they get cleaned up, and it's
not garbage
collection, 'kay?
它们会自动清理，不需要垃圾回收。
It's reference counting.
这就是引用计数。
It's actually counting
references to them
but it's all automatic.
它实际上是计算引用他们的次数，但这都是自动的。
The only thing you ever have to
be maybe
interested in is this weak
business which
你曾经也许唯一感兴趣的是这个weak的功能，
is less than a hundredth of a
percent of
the time.
在小于百分之一的时间。
And for the first four weeks of
this
class, forget about weak.
前四周的课程中，忘掉有关weak的吧。
It'll automatically happen when
you do
this Ctrl+drag, but just ignore
it.
当你使用Ctrl+点击拖动时候，它会自动完成，所以先忽略这个吧。
But the main thing to know is
that all
that memory
但是最主要的事情是知道有关内存管理
management is happening for you.
会发生在你身上的。
Also this, instance variable
right here,
同时，实例变量在这里，
which is a pointer to this
object, notice
there's no ampersands or
通过一个指针指向对象，注意到没有与符号或
stars or any other kind of
syntax that
says this is a pointer.
星或者其他任何语法说这是一个指针。
'Kay?
If you have a instance, variable
or
property or
如果你有一个实例变量或属性或
local variable that is an
object, okay,
局部变量都是一个对象。
it's always a pointer to it cuz
objects
only live in the heap, 'kay?
它总是一个指针，因为对象只在堆中存在着。
So you don't need all that extra
stars and
所以不需要多余的*和&，
ampersand, any of that business
from other
languages, okay?
不要从其他语言中借鉴。
This exclamation point, by the
way, I'm
gonna talk about in a few
minutes,
这个感叹号，顺便说一下，我要谈几分钟
has nothing to do with this
being an
object, okay?
这是和对象不相关的。
This is, this totally separate
thing.
这完全不相干的事情。
We'll get to it.
我们会得到它。
All right.
So let's look at this.
让我们看看这个。
This is the syntax for defining
a
property, 'kay?
这个语法是定义了一个属性，对吗？
An instance variable.
一个实例变量。
And it's very simple.
并且它是如此的简单。
You got var, short for variable
cuz that's
what this is, a variable.
你看到var，它是变量的缩写。
The name, this is the name of
it, display.
这是变量的名称，display
Okay?
That's just the name of this
property.
这个属性的名字是这个。
And then :UILabel!
紧接着就是UILabel。
Is the type, 'kay?
这个是它的类型。
That's the type of this instance
variable.
这个类似是这个实例变量的。
So again, I'll talk about the
exclamation
point later, but
我稍后会讲到那个感叹号，但
obviously this thing is pointing
to this
label so that we can talk to it.
很明显，这是指向label的，我们能这样说。
And we'll be doing that in a
moment.
我们能够这样去做。
'Kay?
Questions?
有什么疑问吗？
All right, let's talk about
another kind
of connection we may,
好的，让我们来谈谈另一种连接，
we can make, let's start putting
some
buttons in our calculator.
我们可以，让我们开始放一些计算器的按钮吧。
So I'm gonna go back to the
Utilities
window, 'kay?
我将要打开这个工具窗口。
By pressing this button over
here,
按下这个按钮，
go down to the bottom, go to the
third tab
over here, the object library.
找到下方的第三个选项的对象目录。
And instead of a label, this
time I'm
gonna drag out a button.
这次拖的不是label，我将要拖动出来一个按钮。
Okay?
I'm gonna put this button here
now.
现在我要把这个按钮放到这里。
Just to be different, I'm not
gonna
initially line it up with a blue
line.
有些不同，我没有初始化蓝色的线。
I'm just gonna put it kinda in
space out
here and
我只是想把它放在这个空间中，
I'll line it up with the blue
line later,
'kay?
将它放在蓝线的下面。
But I don't wanna forget to do
that
though, I always wanna do that.
但我不会忘记做，我总是期望这样。
What I'm gonna do later is to
show you it
can be done.
以后我要做的就是告诉你这是可以做到的。
So, this is gonna be, let's say
this is
gonna be one of our number
buttons.
接着，我们可以说这就是一个数字按钮。
Like the upper left corner of
our keypad
is a 7.
就像键盘左上角的数字7。
Okay?
Again, I have the same thing
over here.
我还需要其他的一些。
Okay?
With the attributes inspector I
can
通过属性设置，我能够
change things like the font.
修改一些字体大小什么的。
Let's make this be 24 point,
let's say.
让我们尝试下尺寸为24的。
I can resize.
我能够修改尺寸。
Notice that when I resize it
will actually
tell me the size,
注意，当我调整它时候，会显示尺寸。
see it saying there what size it
is?
看到它说这是多大的尺寸
I can also set the size maybe
with this
size inspector right here,
我还可以在设置尺寸这里修改，
type it in exactly.
类型的准备。
Maybe 64 by 64, something like
that.
也许64 x 64 看起来更合适。
We don't usually do that.
我们通常不这样做。
We want things to be kinda their
natural
sizes but
我们希望它能够是原始的大小，但
just want to show you that there
are other
inspectors over here.
这里只想向你展示有其他的方法。
So we have this 7.
所以我们有这个7。
Now when this 7 is pressed, what
do we
want to happen?
当7被按下的时候，会发生什么呢？
What we want.
我们想要的。
Numbers just start appearing up
here in
the display, right?
数字出现在需要展示的地方。
So that's something our
controller is
going to have to do.
这就是我们的控制器不得不做的事。
So, when we touch this button,
we kinda
want this button to send a
message to
当我们点击这个按钮，我们想让这个按钮发送信息到
our controller, and we do that
the exact
same way as we did this one,
我们的控制器，跟之前的方式一样，
we hold down control, drag into
our code.
我们按住Ctrl，点击，拖动到代码中。
When we let go though, we're not
going to
an outlet connection this time,
当我们松开时候，我们不想要outlet这个，
because I dont want an instance
variable
here, what i want is a method,
right?
因为我不想要个实例变量，我要的是一个方法对吧？
A function on my class, a
method, everyone
understand the word method I
hope,
我类里的一个函数，方法，我想大家都知道这个词的含义，
okay, so we want it to send an
[INAUDIBLE]
message to our control board, so
我们想让它发送一个消息给控制板
I'm going to pick" action",
[COUGH] losing
my voice here.
所以我选"action",[咳嗽] 有点失声。
Bad time to have a little cold,
but.
关键时刻有点感冒...不过还好。
[SOUND] So I'm doing an action
so
所以在这里我选了 action
an action is a little different
than a
outlet, okay?
action 跟outlet 略有不同。
An outlet means an instance
variable or
outlet 代表一个实例变量
property, action means create a
method for
me.
或者是一个属性，action 则是为我创建了一个方法。
So again it wants to know the
name of the
method.
所以紧接着它要我输入方法的名字。
So what does this thing do?
这个方法要做什么呢？
Well when I press seven, it
appends a
digit onto the end of
当我按7 的时候，
whatever's already in the
display, so I'm
going to call it append,
不管原先显示着什么，都在后面加个7，所以我应该叫它 append...
I could call it append seven,
but I'm
actually going to call it append
digit,
本来应该叫做 append7，但我还是选择appendDigit，
because I want to have one
method that all
of my buttons use.
因为我想所有的按钮都使用这个方法。
All right?
懂了吗？
I don't want to, copy and
pasting a bunch
of methods, that would be really
bad code.
我不想复制粘贴一堆雷同的方法，那样只会把代码变得一团糟。
But if I'm gonna have one
method,
相反我仅仅使用一个方法，
then I need to know which button
is
sending me this message, okay?
所以我就需要知道是哪个按钮发送的这个消息，对吧？
Luckily, when you haven't
actioned a
message being sent here,
在这，这个弹出框里，
you can specify that it has
arguments, you
see right here where it says
arguments?
你可以规定它有没有参数，你看这里它写着arguments了么？
And it can have no arguments or
it can
have the sender.
你可以选择没有参数，或者是 sender。
Which is the button here as the
argument.
sender 的意思就是把这个按钮当作参数。
The only tricky thing here is,
and I'm not
sure why they did this in Xcode.
这里有点诡异，我不懂Xcode 为什么要这样。
Hopefully, they'll change it in
the
future.
希望他们以后能改进下。
By default, the type of that
argument,
which is right here, is any
object.
就是参数的默认类型是 anyobject。
Now, we're gonna talk about any
object
next week.
下周我们会讲什么是anyobject。
But, we don't want any object
here.
不过在这里我们肯定不要anyobject。
We know that the sender is a UI
button, so
我们知道sender 其实是UIButton，
I picked, click this little blue
thing and
switch this to UI button.
点这里选择UIButton。
When you're doing your homework,
if you
forget to switch that to UI
button,
如果你做作业的时候，忘了选成UIButton，
you'll be sad, okay.
你就悲剧了.
So don't forget.
所以，别忘了哦。
And obviously the event that the
message
is gonna be sent on, touch up
inside,
然后很明显，触发事件应该选为 touch up inside，
just means the user touched on
this button
and the touch went up.
意思是你手落在按钮的范围内，手起也在按钮的范围内。
While it was still inside the
button.
意思是你手落在按钮的范围内，手起也在按钮的范围内。
That's all a touch up inside
means there.
这就是touch up inside 的意思。
All right so when I connect
this,
当我点了connect 以后，
I'm gonna get a method with one
argument
which is a sender which is a UI
button.
我就得到了一个方法，有一个参数，类型是UIButton。
So let's take a look.
看看吧，
So here's your first method
declaration in
SWIFT, okay?
它就是你的第一个SWIFT函数。
Again it's got this little IB
action thing
which is kinda like IB outlet.
同样这里有一个叫IBAction的东西，跟IBOutlet 类似。
It puts a little dot in the
gutter.
左边有一个小圆点。
Okay?
So that you can
这样你就可以看见它连的是哪里。
see what this thing is connected
to.
这样你就可以看见它连的是哪里。
So this is the normal, Swift
method
syntax.
这个就是Swift 定义方法的标准语法。
Starts with func because
function,
以func 开头，取了function的缩写。
basically that method is a
function in
class.
它就是我们类里的一个函数了。
[COUGH] Here's the name.
这是它的名字, AppendDigit。
Append digit.
这是它的名字,AppendDigit。
And then in parentheses, all the
arguments
separated by commas.
在括号里，所有参数都用逗号分隔。
We only have one argument,
though.
我们这只有一个参数。
Here's the name of the first
argument.
这个是第一个参数的名字。
That's the name we're going to
use to
access it inside of our method,
and
我们在函数体里就要用到这个名字，
here is the type.
这是它的类型。
Okay?
It's a UI button.
懂了么？类型是UIButton。
I, notice no exclamation point
there, by
the way.
先暂时无视这个叹号。
Okay if this had a return value,
if this
method returned something this
one doesn't
如果这个函数有返回值，虽然这里没有。
[COUGH] but if it returned
something, it
would look like this arrow the
return type
我说的是如果它有的话，这里就写这样的箭头。
okay so that's how you specify a
return
type.
这样就定义了它的返回类型。
Okay, pretty simple the syntax
and then
inside here we just type,
看见了么？非常简单的语法。
well whatever we want this thing
to do
when one of these buttons is
touched.
继续看我们的函数，当点击了其中一个按钮，
So what do we want it to do?
我们要让他干什么。
Well, okay, first of all before
we do
that, let's go ahead and make
more of
在此之前，我们先多弄几个按钮。
these buttons because I need
seven, eight,
nine, four, five, six, all this.
我们还需要其他的按钮，4,5,6,7 这些。
So let's copy and paste the
button.
可以复制粘贴。
When I copy and
paste the button, notice I'm
using the
blue lines to put it perfectly
lined up.
注意我用这些蓝线来对齐。
Okay, also notice that it there
also
sending this message.
注意，他们都发送同一个消息，触发同一个函数。
All right, see how their both
sending the
message, because when I copy and
因为拷贝按钮的时候连同这些信息也一起拷贝了。
paste, it copied that aspect of
it as
well.
因为拷贝按钮的时候连同这些信息也一起拷贝了。
So there's another one, I could
select all
three of these and
可以一次选三个，一起拷贝。
copy and paste, okay, I could
select all
six of these and copy and paste.
6个一起选
So I can quickly make, my entire
keypad.
这样快速得把键盘造出来了。
Just need to edit the title.
只需要改改title。
Now, if while I'm editing these
titles,
sometimes you're clicking around
in
如果你像现在这样，做些改动，点来点去。
here and, you know, you're not a
very
accurate clicker.
不小心没点准。
[LAUGH] Or, you know, you just
get out,
out of control clicking here,
and oh,
手一滑把控件拖飞了。
you moved it out of the way.
Okay?
怎么办？
No problem, you can just put it
right back
in.
没关系，只要把它再拖回原地。
Okay, use the blue lines to your
advantage.
那些蓝色的辅助线会帮你个大忙。
And we'll put our zero down
here.
把0 放在这。
And I don't need these buttons
so I'm just
hit, selecting it, hitting
delete.
选中，多余的按钮，点 Delete。
That's how you can get rid of
something.
就这么删东西。
And I promised I was gonna put
these all
on blue lines, so I'm gonna do
that.
我说过要把他们对齐蓝线。
I'm gonna put it right
underneath the
zero.
把他们放在0 标签控件的底下。
So here's a blue line that means
underneath the zero, and
这条蓝线就表明我可以放在标签底下。
then I'm going to put at this
edge.
让它对起左边这条蓝线。
So now you can see that the blue
lines are
not just the edges, but
你可以发现，这些蓝线不仅在调整边缘的时候出现。
they are other objects, like the
other
objects in the keypad and
在调整其他对象，比如这些按钮的时候，他们也会出现。
also now the title, the display
rather at
the top.
同样，标题，标签这些也同样受用。
So I've got all these buttons,
they're all
sending this message append
digit.
现在按钮齐了，他们都发送 appendDigit 这个消息。
So I need to figure out which
one is
sending it,
所以我就需要分辨出是哪个按钮发送的消息。
so that I can do the right
thing.
然后针对性的做相应的功能。
So let's start writing some code
inside
the method.
现在让我们来往这个方法里添加代码。
So the first thing I'm going to
do is
declare a local variable,
首先，我要申明一个本地变量。
it's just a local variable
inside this
method.
就是方法内部的本地变量。
I'm going to do that by saying
let digit
equal.
let digit =
So I want this local variable to
be the
digit that was pressed.
我想让这个变量表示我们输入的数字。
Okay.
So, first thing that's quite
different
here is, what's let?
这里值得注意的是，这个let 是什么？
Okay?
嗯哼？
Why isn't this var, right?
为什么不是跟上面那个一样的var？
Cuz var means variable, what the
heck does
let mean?
因为var 是变量的意思，那let 是什么鬼？
Well let is exactly the same as
var except
it's a constant.
其实 let 跟 var 差不多，只不过 let 代表常量。
Which means you're going to sign
this
right off the bat, and
意味着一旦你为它设置了初值。
it's never going to change in
this method.
它在这个方法内就再也不能被改变了。
Now Swift makes a big deal about
this, and
这在SWFT里很重要。
I love this feature, because if
I'm
reading this code,
我大爱这个特性，
I know the digit is never going
to change
all, this might be, you know.
因为当我读代码的时候，我知道它不会变，而上面那个（var）会变。
It might have a dozen lines of
code.
假设你的方法里有几十行代码，
Which by the way,
顺便提一下，
you shouldn't have very many
methods, with
many more lines of code then
that.
你最好别在一个方法里面塞太多的代码，
Okay?
You want people to be able to
你应该让人清楚明了的知道你这个方法要做的是什么事情。
kind of see what a method's
doing.你应该让人清楚明了的知道你这个方法要做的是什么事情。
You can use other methods,
你可以添加其他的方法，
call other methods if you need
to get more
code in there.
然后通过调用那些方法来实现更多的逻辑。
so.
回过头来。
Here I can de-,
rely on that not changing.
因为有了这个“不变” 的性质，
That's big for readability.
代码的可读性得到了很大的提升。
You'll be surprised how much
more readable
it makes the code, to know that
this is a,
你会惊叹仅仅知道哪些是变量，哪些是常量，就会对代码的可阅读性带来这么大的提升。
local variable, but it's
constant.
你会惊叹仅仅知道哪些是变量，哪些是常量，就会对代码的可阅读性带来这么大的提升。
Only set at the beginning.
只需要申明的时候加个关键字就行。
Yeah.
Is there a reason, constants and
[学生提问] 对于像变量、常量这些东西，这里为什么都用相同的命名规范？
like, variables have the same
naming
convention.
[学生] 对于像变量、常量这些东西，这里为什么都使用相同的命名规范？
Since [UNKNOWN] like Java there.
因为比如说Java 会用“全部大写”或者“全部小写”来区别这些概念。
Like the naming conventions like
all caps
or lowercase.
因为比如说Java 会用“全部大写”或者“全部小写”来区别这些概念。
Yeah.
So, yeah.
[提问完毕]
The question is, why don't I
call digit
like all caps digit, or
这位同学的问题是，为什么不把 digit 写成 DIGIT，
something like that, so I know
it's a
constant.
以此来区分他是不是常量。
That would be a programming
style thing.
这算是编程风格的问题，
Generally in Swift they don't do
that.
但在SWIFT 里，我们通常不这样做。
And, I'll show you why that is
in a
moment.
我之后会给你们演示，
Why you don't really need to do
that.
为什么我们不需要通过玩弄命名规范来区别这些概念，
Because you can very quickly
find out the
declaration of
因为你可以非常快速的找到每个变量的定义，
any symbol anywhere with one
click, and
you'll see that.
只需要点一下鼠标就一目了然。
Good question though.
问得不错！
All right, so I wanna let the
digit, equal
the number that's on the,
所以，接下来我要 let digit = 被触发的按钮上的那个数字
the sending button.
So I'm gonna have to send a
message to
this button.
所以我要向那个按钮发送一个消息。
Okay?
Gonna have to somehow access
this button.
对吧？我们得访问这个按钮对象。
So I'm gonna have to do sender,
something.
我就打 sender 然后..
Give me what your title is,
okay?
拿到他的title 对吧？
So this is a good time to talk
about the
documentation.
现在就是讲讲文档的好时机了
[COUGH].
[咳咳]
Because being a good iOS
developer,
想要成为一名好的iOS开发者，
really demands that you are good
at
navigating the documentation.
熟练地使用文档是必须的。
Luckily, the documentation is
really well
plugged in to Xcode.
幸运的是，Xcode 已经完美地嵌入了文档支持。
For example, if I wanna find out
about
button,
比如，我想看看按钮的文档。
all I need to do is hold down
the option
key.
我只要按住option。
Okay?
And watch what happens now.
看见有什么变化么？
As I mouse over things,
当我的鼠标移动到文本上方时，他们底下就会出现一条蓝色的虚线。
everything, it turns blue with a
dashed
blue line under it, okay?
当我的鼠标移动到文本上方时，他们底下就会出现一条蓝色的虚线。
If I click on it,
如果我点击。
it gives me a little blurb from
the
documentation about this thing.
他就弹出一个文档的摘要。
So it's saying, you know,
here's, button
is a class.
他说这是button， 这是一个类，
Here's its inheritance.
这里有他的继承关系
Here's a little bit of what it
does.
这里是关于他的功能。
And really awesome at the bottom
here,
最棒的是在最后这里，
here's a link that takes you to
the
detailed documentation.
这是一个指向详细文档的链接。
So I'm gonna click this little
link right
here.
我点击他。
It's going to be up a
documentation
window, with UI button in it,
hello?
他就打开了UIButton的文档窗口...咦？
Did I not click that right thing
here,
我没点错吧？
oh I hope I don't have a network
issue
here.
不会是网络出问题了吧..
hm, okay well, I guess I'm not
connected
to the network,
好吧..我猜我的网络出问题了..
that's the problem, so it's
getting this
off the network.
果然，没有联上网..
Okay so.
好吧。
Imagine that there were
documentation here
and, it would have along this
side here
那就想象一下..文档出现在了这里。
on the left all the instance
variables or
properties and methods of u i
button.
在窗口的左边，就会出现很长的一列关于UIButton的属性，变量，方法什么的。
And you could click on any one,
and
你可以点击他们，然后就可以看见完整的描述。
in there we'd have a full
description of
it here.
你可以点他们，然后就可以看见完整的描述。
And all the types that it
referenced you
could click on it here, and
所有文档间的引用你都可以点击，
basically it's a hyper linked
documentation [UNKNOWN].
它本质上就是一些文档间的超链接，
As you can imagine.
你可以想象得到的。
I'll try to get the networking
working on
Wednesday and we'll take a look
at this.
我争取在下周三把网络问题搞定，到时候我们就能一睹芳容了。
But if I was looking in here,
假设我能看到文档的话，
I'd look down in the section
that says
getting the button's current
state, and
我会在这里找到一些如何获取UIButton状态的信息。
I'd find that there is an
instance
property there called current
title.
我会找到一个叫做currentTitle 的属性。
Okay?
It's unfortunate I'm not going
to
很遗憾没能能演示这个流程
link these things.
很遗憾没能演示这个流程。
But.
不过问题不大。
So how do we access, property or
call a
method in another object,
那么怎么访问到一个对象的属性、方法呢？
will look exactly the same
whether you
call it a method or
答案是，访问属性和调用函数的方式是一模一样的。
accessing a property, which is
you use
dot.
访问属性，你用点(.)
Okay.
It's the same syntax that's used
in
这跟大多数语言是一样的，都用点号来访问成员。
a lot of languages is to, to do
dot.
这跟大多数语言是一样的，都用点号来访问成员。
And so when you do that, Xcode
is going to
say, oh,
当你在Xcode里打一个点的时候，他就说，呐，
well, here's all the things
button knows
how to do.
这里是所有UIButton可访问的成员。
Okay?
看见了么？
And as you can see, button knows
how to do
a lot of things.
你可以发现，UIButton 能做很多事情，
Because it inherits from a
class, it
inherits from a class,
这是因为它继承于一个类，它的父类又继承于另一个类，不停继承。
it inherits from a class, that
all have
lots of methods in them.
所以累计起来就有很多方法可供调用。
So when I looked at that
documentation.
所以当我查看了文档以后，
I've found that current title
was the
thing I wanted.
我知道currentTitle 这个属性正是我想要的。
Now notice as I start to type a
c, it's
already cutting down
注意这里我打个字母c，它会帮我过滤出那些开头是c 的选择。
the things that could be
starting with a
c, and then c u, they cut down
even more.
然后接着打 cu，它有棒我过滤掉了一些。
I can type tab, to get to the
first
ambiguity point, then I can type
t.
我可以点Tab 键，前进到第一个歧义点，然后接着打 t。
Okay?
And then tab again, and I'm here
at
current title and then I can
press return.
然后再敲Tab键，得到currentTitle，然后打Enter。
Okay?
So there it is.
好了。
Digit equals sender current
title.
digit = sender.currentTitle
so, what's going on here in
terms of did,
descender title.
我们现在拿到了sender 的currentTitle然后呢？
Let's go ahead and print this
out to the
console just to see what's going
on.
我们把它打印出来，看看他里面是什么东西。
So I'm gonna print lin.
这里使用println 函数。
At which is a function, a global
function
that takes a string.
他是一个全局函数，以一个string 为参数。
So I give it a string.
所以我就给他一个string。
And inside that string, I'll
type mm,
在string里，我打 "digit = "..
digit equals and now I wanna
embed the
value of digit in this string.
让他等于digit 的值。
And Swift has a really cool
feature which
is backslash open parentheses
这里介绍一个很酷的SWFIT特性，就是，
close parentheses.
如果你在字符串里里放进这个 "\()"，然后你就可以在括号里面放入一个表达式。
If you put that in a string, and
then
inside there you put some
expression, then
如果你在字符串里里放进这个 "\()"，然后你就可以在括号里面放入一个表达式。
it will evaluate that expression
turn it
into a string, and embed it in
the string.
SWIFT 就会对这个表达式求值，然后把值转换成string，最后嵌入到那个字符串里。
Okay, so its really easy to
print lin
values by
所以用这个 "\()" 语法可以很方便的println 一个对象的值。
using this backslash
parenthesis.
所以用这个 "\()" 语法可以很方便的println 一个对象的值。
Okay?
So let's go ahead and run and
现在让我们编译运行。
see what happens when we press
these
buttons to see what kind of
result we get.
看看我们按按钮的时候会打印出什么结果。
It's not going to be quite what
we expect,
but let's see.
结果可能会跟预期的有所不同。
Alright so, here's our BUY we
got our
buttons that's a good start.
这里是我们的UI，有了一些按钮，看起来不错。
And now, and console, where's
the console?
但是控制台呢？现实输出结果的控制台去哪了？
Watch this.
I'm going to press a button
five.
看好了，当我点击 5 按钮的时候。
The console appears at the
bottom here.
控制台就在下面出现了。
See this down here.
看见了嘛，在底栏。
This is the console.
这就是控制台。
And it's saying digit equals,
hm, optional
five.
这里显示了， digit 等于..呃... Optional("5")
Okay.
好吧。
How about a nine?
看看 9 呢？
They're all optional.
也是Optional 的。
What the heck is going on here?
这是什么鬼?
Okay.
好～
This is crucial to understanding
Swift.
接下来我们将要理解一个SWFIT 里的重要概念。
This is probably the most
important thing
to understand that
这个概念初学者常常会搞错，但在SWFIT 里他非常重要。
people don't quite get right
from the
start.
这个概念初学者常常会搞错，但在SWFIT 里他非常重要。
So we're really going to focus
here on
understanding what
所以接下来我们集中精力，好好的理解这个 Optional 到底是什么意思。
optional means right there.
Okay?
注意听。
So let's go back to our code.
先回到代码。
And look at this, oh and by the
way it,
when the console appears down
here,
顺便提一下，当控制台出现了以后，
you can make it go away with
this little
button, or
你可以用这个按钮把它隐藏掉。
you can just drag it out of the
way okay?
或者也可以用鼠标把它拖走。
But sometimes it's nice to have
that
console still there, so
不过让它一直显示在那里也挺好，
you can look at your output
while you're
you know reacting to whatever
you found,
你可以随时看见你的输出，及时察觉问题。
in fact we will leave that up
there, so
you can see the optionals.
我就不隐藏他了，让你可以看见我们现在要讲的东西。
Alright, so, what's going on
here?
言归正传。
Well, what's happening here is,
well,
first of all,
首先，
don't you find this a little bit
odd, let
digit, I didn't put a type.
你有没有发现一个奇怪的地方？ 这里 let digit = ... 我并没有给digit 一个类型。
You see that?
How, what type is digit?
那这个digit 到底是什么类型呢？
Okay, well there's no type in
there, no
type information whatsoever, so.
你可能会想，这里没有指定任何类型，难道SWFIT 支持无类型变量？
Does Swift have untyped
variables?
你可能会想，这里没有指定任何类型，难道SWFIT 支持无类型变量？
No, it's exact opposite.
错！恰恰相反。
Swift is very strongly typed.
SWIFT 是非常非常强类型的。
Okay.
All variables have a type.
所有变量都有他的类型。
You have to specify type.
你必须给变量规定一个类型。
But, Swift is also incredibly
good at
what's called type inference.
然后，SWFIT 有一个非常强大的特性，叫做类型推导。
So it can infer the type from
the context.
这样它就能通过当前上下文来推断出变量的类型。
So here I let digit equal
whatever this
is, this current title, and
所以，当我写digit = ...无论我等号后面写什么，
so it just made digit be the
same type as
this.
它都能将digit 设置成等号后面那个东西的类型。
Okay.
懂了么？
Now back to the question
earlier, so what
type is that?
回到之前的问题，那么这个到底是什么类型？
Well, if I hold down option,
okay, just
like we used option to
我可以按住Option 键，就像查看文档那样，
go look into the documentation,
we can
also option click on our own
variables.
按住Option 键点击我们的变量，看看他是常量还是变量
To see are they constant?
Are they variables?
按住Option 键点击我们的变量，看看他是常量还是变量
And what type are they?
还可以看看他们是什么类型。
So watch this.
看这个。
Option click.
按住Option 然后点～
It says digit is of type string
question
mark.
他说，digit 是 “string?” 类型的。
Okay?
String question mark.
嗯，string 后面有个问号。
That question mark means
optional.
这个问号的意思是——“可选”
So there is a type in Swift,
it's a type,
called optional.
在SWIFT 里面，有一种类型，叫做 optional
Okay.
Optional, that type can have
only two
values.
Optional 这种类型，只有两个值。
One value is not set.
一个值叫：未设。
Okay, this optional is not set,
there has
never been set or someone has
代表着这个值还没有被任何人设置过，或者，有人故意把它设置成了“未设”状态。
set it to the not set state,
they unset it
if you want to think about it
that way.
代表着这个值还没有被任何人设置过，或者，有人故意把它设置成了“未设”状态。
So optional one value is not
set, we call
that there's a, symbol for
当一个Optional 的变量是“未设”状态时，
it in here called nil, N, I, L,
okay?
有一个符号用来表示这个状态，这个符号叫做nil, N, I, L。
That means not set, that's the
value of an
optional not set.
nil 就是“未设”的意思，就是optional 变量在“未设”状态下的值。
That's the only thing nil means
in Swift
is option this is an optional,
在SWFIT 里，nil 只有这一个意义，就是说这个变量是Optional 的，而且它的状态是“未设”
the value of an optional that is
not set.
在SWFIT 里，nil 只有这一个意义，就是说这个变量是Optional 的，而且它的状态是“未设”
What's the other value that an
optional
could have well the other value
is.
那Optional 变量的另一种值是是什么呢？
Something, it's set to
something, okay.
“有值”，就是说他被设置赋了一个值。
And the type of that something
is what,
那“有值”的这个值，是什么类型呢？
is specified next to the
question mark
string.
就是“？”前面那个东西代表的类型。
So really you can almost think
of the
question mark there, that's the
type
所以，你可以这样想：
optional, and that string to the
left is
just saying if this optional is
set,
问号左边的那个string，就表示，如果这个Optional 变量被赋了值的话，那么他的类型就是string。
what type of thing is it set to,
in this
case a string.
问号左边的那个string，就表示，如果这个Optional 变量被赋了值的话，那么他的类型就是string。
So we would call this an
optional string.
所以，我们可以称其为“Optional String”
But it's really an optional,
it's not a
string that can be nil,
但是他实际上确确实实是Optional 类型的，他不是一个可以为nil 的string。
it's an optional that can be a
string.
他是Optional 类型，只不过可以被赋值为stirng。
Everybody cool with that
sentence?
好好理解这句话。
That's an important sentence to
understand, okay.
理解这个含义非常非常的关键。
So, this got to be an optional
because
this current title method right
here,
所以在这里，currentTitle 返回的值肯定是Optional 类型的。
returns an optional string,
let's look at
that.
我们来看看。
So I'm going to press Option down
here,
click.
按住Option 点currentTitle。
Look at this, this is the
documentation
for it.
看看他的文档。
It's an instance variable a, a,
property
on UI button.
这是一个实例变量，UIButton的属性
Name is current title.
名字是current title
The type is string, question mark.
类型是string，问号标记。
And this little get means it's read-only.
而这里的“get”表示这个是只读的。
I can only get the current title.
我只能获得current title。
I can't set it, there are other ways to set a button's title.
但是我不能设置，有其他方式进行设置。
You can't set it with this method or this property.
你不能通过这个方法或者属性进行设置。
So it's an optional, so that's why this ended up being an optional all right.
所以这是一个选项，这就是为什么最后是一个选项。
Well, that's all wonderful.
嗯，这非常不错。
How do I get the string?
我怎么获取这个string呢？
I don't want it optional, I want that button's string.
我不需要它的选项，我要的是这个按钮的标题。
And the way you do that is you unwrap the optional, meaning you look in there and
方法就是你可以打开这个方法，意思是你正在
get the val, the associated value, with exclamation point, okay.
用“!”从里边获取关联的值。
What happens if I put that exclamation point there?
如果我把感叹号放在这里会怎么样？
Well first of all, let me show you that when I put that exclamation point,
首先我先会展示给你们看，我把感叹号放在这里
look what happened to digit, I'm Option-clicking on digit.
看看会有什么变化，我现在点击数字。
It's not an optional anymore.
它不再是选项了。
Digit turned to a string because I unwrapped the optional that
数字变成了string，因为我打开了选项
came back from current title, got the string out of there.
从当前的标题里的到了string。
But what happens if this is nil?
但是如果这是个nil值会怎么样？
What happened if this optional is nil?
如果选项是nil会发生什么事情？
In other words the button option has never been set, crash, 'kay,
换句话说，就是这些按钮选项没有设置会怎么样？对的，会崩溃。
crashes your program, so if you use exclamation point to unwrap an optional,
所以如果你使用"!"号来打开一个选项的时候。
and that optional's current value is not set, nil, then it will crash your program.
并且这个选项没有设值为空的时候，你的程序会崩溃。
Now a lot of you might be like whoa, I'm, my products are gonna be crashing all over
现在你们中的不少人肯定在想，怎么我的东西老是崩溃？
the place and, because there's a lot of optionals in iOS, I mean a lot, okay?
这是因为iOS有着非常多的选项，记住是非常多。
Most things are probably optionals, because most things, it make sense,
多数东西都是选项，因为这些东西都是有意义的。
they can be in an not set state at some point.
他们能在一些情况下出于不需设值的状态。
And yeah, in this case though, maybe you want your program to crash, okay?
在这个情况下，说不定你就希望你的程序崩溃？对不对？
You might want your program to crash, because if you had a button, that never
你也许就是希望自己的程序崩溃，因为你有一个按键，
had its title set, and it's sending a pen digit to your controller, you probably
但是它的标题从未设值，并且它传了一个数字给你的控制器
wanna have that crash, so you can find that bug, before you ship your program.
在你分发你的程序之前，你就能找到bug，所以你希望它崩溃。
You see why sometimes fra, crashing is good?
现在你知道为什么有时候程序崩溃是个好事吧。
Now if you don't wanna crash, there's a way to get around that as well.
现在如果你不想你的程序崩溃，这里有一个方法来解决。
And I'll show you that a little bit later.
我等一下就和你们说。
But for now understanding that that's what this exclamation point does.
但是现在，先弄明白这个感叹号是干什么的。
It unwraps that optional and crashes if it's nil.
它打开了选项，如果它是nil就崩溃。
But if it's not nil, it gets to the string or
但如果不是空，它是得到string还是
whatever the optional type is out of there for you.
给你其他的选项类型？
So now let's go ahead and run again and
所以让我们继续，重新运行一次
we're gonna see that digit equals is gonna say the number, 'kay?
我们将看看是不是能得到相等的数字？
It's got the string off the current title, no more optional in there, okay?
我们得到了当前的标题，没有更多的选项了。
Good?
看上去不错。
All right, so, now, what are we gonna do with that digit?
好的，现在，我们要用这些按钮做什么呢？
We got the digit,
我们已经能得到数字。
we want to append it onto the end of this display right here, okay.
我们希望按的数字能显示在这里的末尾。
And so let's just do that by saying display, dot.
所以让我们输入display.
Now, again, if we have the documentation,I'd go look in the documentation and
现在继续，如果我们查文档。
it would say oh, there's a property on UILabel, which is what display is,
它会告诉我们，UILabel有一个属性
display is a UILabel.
负责显示UILabel应该显示的什么。
There's a property and it' called text.
这个属性叫做text
See it right there?
就在这里。
And actually, you can even see right here, the type of that, it's an optional as
而且实际上，输入这个，你能在这里看到，这是一个选项。
well, because this label's text might not have been set either, okay?
所以这个label的text还没有设值。
So it has to be an optional string, okay?
所以这里是选项string。
So I'm just gonna set that equal now, display that text as an optional, so
所以我现在要用等号设值，显示的text作为一个选项
what values can I send it to,set it to?
什么值可以设给它？
I could set it to nil, that would be legal because it's an optional,
我可以设成nil，因为它是一个选项，是完全合法的。
see, no warnings, no errors.
看，没有警告也没有错误。
That would clear out that display.
这将什么也不显示。
It would not be set to anything, or
它不能设值成其他东西
I can set it to a string because it's an optional string.
我能给它设一个string值，因为它是一个选项string。
So I'm going to set it to a string and the string I'm going to set it
所以我将把它设值一个string
to is display.text, what's currently in there, plus digit, okay?
这个string我设置成display.text，这里加个数字。
So I'm going to append that digit on.
这样子就能增加数字了。
Let's get rid of that.
让我们摆脱删掉这句。
Okay, now, this has an error here.
好吧，现在又有一个错误。
Why does this have an error?
这个错误是为什么呢？为什么这里有个错误呢？
Anyone volunteer why this is an error?
有谁自愿回答这里为什么有个错误？
See it's pointing right here.
发现错误指向这里。
There's an error, back there.
这里有个错误，后面那位同学回答。
The display.text is an optional string.
display.text是一个选项string。
Bingo. Because display.text right here is not
答对了，因为这里的display.tex它不是个string。
a string, it's an optional, and you can't add a string to an optional.
你不能将一个string加在一个选项上。
You can only add strings to other strings.
你只能将一个string加在另外的string上。
So we need to turn this into a string by unwrapping it.
所以我们通过打开选项，将选项转变为string。
And again, yes, this would crash if the display currently has nothing in it,
对的，这个东西会crash，如果display没有值。
it's not set, okay?
现在还没有设值。
Are we cool with that?
大家都了解这个了吧？
So let's run again.
再让我们运行一次。
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[背景音]
All right.
好的。
So now 5, oh, it put the 5 on there.
所以现在点击5，噢，5显示在这里了。
6, excellent.
点击6，好极了。
It's kinda working.
它能够工作了。
I don't really like that 0 though.
这个0在这里我很不喜欢。
That's kinda weak, 0, 5, 6.
这里就有点不对劲了，5和6前面有个0。
That should not,
这样子是不对的。
that 0 should've gotten cleared out, right, when I first typed that 5.
这个0应该在我按下5的时候就清除掉。
And that's because we really need some way in our controller to know whether we're in
这是因为我们确实需要一些方法让我们的controller知道我们是否在
the middle of typing a number right now.
一个数字膻中输入数字。
Because if we're in the middle of typing a number, we want to append, but
因为如果我们在一个已有数字中部输入数字，我们是希望数字加在输入的地方的。
if we're not in the middle of typing a number,
但是如果我们不用从一个数字的中部进行输入。
we want to start a new number, right?
也就是我们想要从头开始输入一个新的数字。
So, let's do that, and I'm going to do that by adding a property, okay?
所以，让我们通过添加一个属性实现这个效果。
Var userIsInTheMiddleOfTypingANumber , which you might say,
设个叫做“userIsInTheMiddleOfTypingANumber”的变量，你也许会说
oh my God, that terrible variable, now I have to type that over and over.
天哪，这么糟糕的变量名字，每次都得这么输入还不得累死？
This is the last time I'll ever have to type that, okay?
其实下次用到这个变量我可不需要输入这么多的。
Because Xcode is always going to escape complete it for me, okay?
因为下次用到Xcode会帮我自动补齐的。
So long names are perfectly fine, in terms of typing load anyway.
所以这么长的名字没有问题。
So I like this name so I'm gonna keep it.
我就挺喜欢这个名字的，就这么用了。
And it's a bool, okay.
这是一个布尔型数值。
So I'm typing its, giving its type.
所以输入它的类型。
So here's var name type, and notice, look at this little error right here, 'kay.
命名完变量的名字和类型，注意看这里，有一个小错误标记。
Okay, sometimes you're gonna get errors in Swift that are completely incomprehensible
好吧，有时候你用Swift会遇到难以理解的错误。
to you because you haven't learned enough of Swift.
但是这是因为你对Swift的了解不够深入。
This one's kind of like that.
这个错误就是因为这个。
You see, it says, class view controller has no initializers.
你看，这里说类视图控制器没有初始化。
And that's because, and pay attention, in Swift all properties
请注意，这是因为，在Swift里
have to be initialized when the object is initialized.
一个对象没有初始化，那么对象的属性都不会初始化。
Okay, you can't have a property just sitting around not initialized,
所以你不能用没有初始化的属性。
they have to have a value.
它们需要一个值。
Now if they're an optional,
现在，它们是一个选项。
their value can be nil, but they have to have some value.
它们的值可以为空，但是它们必须有值。
So we can't have this have no value.
所以我们不能在它们没有值前使用。
Now there's two ways to give it a value.
有两种方法给它设值。
One is, with an initializer.
一种就是用初始化。
Unfortunately, I'm not gonna teach that to you until next week, so
但是不幸的是，这个方法要下周才讲。
you can't do it that way.
你还不能用这个方法。
Another way is just to say what it equals right here, okay?
所以另外一种方法就是对其直接赋值。
And boom, gets rid of all our errors, obviously we don't start out in
一下子，  所有问题都解决了。
the middle of typing a number,so we're good to go here, all right.
很明显用户不会从中间输入数字，所以从这一点出发
So now we have, we know whether the use is in the middle of typing a number.
现在我们知道了用户是否会从中间输入数字。
We can go down here and say if the user,
我们能从这里继续深入，如果说用户
now again, I'm just gonna hit Tab to jump past this, maybe a couple times.
按一下Tab，可能要花点时间，找到这个
But if the user's in the middle of typing a number,
但是如果用户从中间输入数字。
then we'll do what we were doing before.
那就和刚才我们已经做得一样处理。
Otherwise, we're just gonna set the display.text equal to the new digit we
另外，如果我们计划设置display.text为一个新的数字
just typed, 'kay?
只需要输入这个：
And we're gonna say that the user is now in the middle of typing a number.
这句表示用户现在在数字的中间输入数字。
Question?
什么问题？
Why would we have to do
[INAUDIBLE] to
display it?
Initialize?
Why did we not have to initialize this?
为什么我们部初始化这个？
That's a fantastic question and
这是个不错的问题
I'm gonna talk about that on Wednesday cuz there's only one minute left.
我将在下周三说这个问题，现在只剩下一分钟了。
But that is a great question and it'll also, when I talk about it,
在我下次说到的时候，这依然是个很好的问题。
I'm gonna tell you why this is an exclamation point and not a question mark.
我说一下为什么这里是个感叹号而不是个问好。
Because I told you that optionals are made with question marks.
因为我之前说过选项都是用问号标记的。
So why the heck is this optional?
但是为什么这个东西是选项
Cuz that's what it is, an exclamation point, so we'll talk about that next time.
因为可是个感叹号，我们下次课再说这个问题。
All right, so let's go ahead and run one last time here.
所以让我们下次课继续。
And hopefully this is gonna, this 0 will be cleared out, it is and
我们之前希望这个0可以正确的清除掉，看来没问题，看看这个
hopefully this will continue to append, it is.
希望这个可以正常的增加，看来也没问题。
So we're in a great spot right here, we've got a calculator,
我们今天已经有了一个不错的开始，我们将会做一个计算器。
we can enter numbers in it, next step is, we gotta make it do some calculating, and
我们已经能够输入数字了，下一步我们将让其能够计算。
we're gonna do that next time so I will see you then.
我们下节课再做，大家下节课见。
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.
想浏览更多？请访问stanford.edu。